<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the seven wise mistrisses of Rome ... wherein, the treachery of evil counsel is discovered, the innocency of harmless virgins cleared, and the wisdom of seven wise women displayed, to the wonder of their own nation, and the administration of all the world.</title>
            <title>Seven wise mistresses of Rome</title>
            <author>Howard, Thomas, 17th/18th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44659</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4376</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12187150</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12187150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44659)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 107:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the seven wise mistrisses of Rome ... wherein, the treachery of evil counsel is discovered, the innocency of harmless virgins cleared, and the wisdom of seven wise women displayed, to the wonder of their own nation, and the administration of all the world.</title>
                  <title>Seven wise mistresses of Rome</title>
                  <author>Howard, Thomas, 17th/18th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[186] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M. Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface by Thomas Howard, to whom the work has been attributed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chapbooks.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:1"/>
            <figure>
               <head>The Empreſs and her Daughter, with the Seven Wiſe Miſtriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY Of the Seven Wiſe Miſtriſſes OF ROME.</p>
            <p>Whoſe Names were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Halicuja,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mardula,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cicre,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Penthiſilia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Debora,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dejanara,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Boadicia.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, the Treachery of Evil Counſel is diſcovered, the Innocency of harmleſs Virgins cleared, and the Wiſdom of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Wiſe Women diſplayed, to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their own Nation, and the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. Wright,</hi> at the Kings Head in the <hi>Old Bailey.</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat thou findeſt written in this ſmall piece, or little Volume, was written for thy benefit, whereby thou mayeſt learn to know what canting, what deceits, and juggling Devices were commonly uſed in Ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, by powerfull Combinations
<pb facs="tcp:55822:3"/>and violent proſecutions, Honour being the ſubject to make them ambitious; but the ſubject of my Diſcourſe is Counſel and Wiſdom: that is rarety not novelty, attended both by Vice and Vertue, to teach thee how to imbrace the one, and to ſhun the other. And therefore I have laboured like unto the Bee to extract and gather a little Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into a little Hive, being the firſt-fruits of my Labours between Vice and Vertue, collected into an eaſie and ſmall Method for the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Seller, the Eaſe of the Buyer, and the Pleaſure of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And though it is ſhort, yet it is ſweet, and of ſundry Counſels and Conſultations, from the ſubtil
<pb facs="tcp:55822:3"/>Judge on the Bench of Juſtice, to the harmleſs Lady in her Cabinet of Innoceny: and from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour upon his Throne of Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to the Beggar in his Cave of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; and therefore in all matters and in all actions thou goeſt about, here is the platform of Sincerity, Truth, Zeal and Fidelity; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Treaſon is diſcovered, Truth is advanced, Treachery is executed, Vertue is exalted, and Vice is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. And for the due obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of theſe Precepts, and the further encouragement for thee to read them, minde theſe four rules.</p>
            <p>If thou wouldſt be Wiſe, here are Counſels to adviſe thee.</p>
            <p>If thou wouldſt be Vertuous,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:4"/>here are Preſidents to give thee.</p>
            <p>If thou wouldſt be Hiſtorical, here are Rules to direct thee.</p>
            <p>If thou wouldſt be Viceous, here are Examples before thee both Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane.</p>
            <p>From all which thou wilt learn, Vanity to contemn it; Death to expect it; Judgement to avoid it; Hell to eſcape it; and Heaven to deſire it.</p>
            <p>It is collected in way of Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Declarations to a Moral Senſe; and if thou wouldſt ask the Author from whence he gathered all theſe varieties of Delights? he doth anſwer, from various ſorts of Hiſtories: as, <hi>Plato, Virgil, Ovid, Dares,</hi> old <hi>Homer,</hi> and divers
<pb facs="tcp:55822:4"/>others, to relate all is needleſs; and in their Works have I been groveling ſome certaine yeares to finde out the remarkable Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations which I have here expos'd to the publique view of the world. For in Hiſtories are to be found numerous Delights pleaſing the Fancy, expelling Melancholly, ſharpning the Wit, illuminating the Underſtanding, and refining the Tongue to the purity of all Oratory.</p>
            <p>The due obſervation of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries learns both Carriage and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, and is able out of the roughneſs of Barbariſm, to raiſe man to the nobleſt height of all Gentilities, Courtſhips, and Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:5"/>and to carry on Deſignes of united Hearts at greateſt diſtance: and whoſoever maintains his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with Learning, muſt of neceſſity with Hiſtorical Humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts; and though their Bodies are abſent, yea, and haply rotten in their graves, or conſumed to duſt and aſhes many hundred years ago, yet having their Works before us, we do diſpute, confer, and argue, yea, and know their hearts and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations in matters both Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and Civil, as abſolute as if their perſons were alive and in our preſence.</p>
            <p>From Hiſtories we learn by way of tradition, to know what was done a thouſand years ago, and ten
<pb facs="tcp:55822:5"/>thouſand miles diſtant from the place, as well, nay and better then thouſands which lived in thoſe very dayes, and where the actions were done: Therefore Hiſtory ought to be praiſed not contemned; for it doth encourage Youth through the pleaſantneſs of the Story, whereby he doth ſooner attain to his Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tongue, and is ſtill more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to read further. For many thouſands at School, in their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, are more naturally given to learn firſt Hiſtorical Fables, by which they ſooner come to read perfect, then to begin firſt in hard Books appertaining to Divine Knowledge; which made that rare and learned Schollar <hi>Aeſop,</hi> to put
<pb facs="tcp:55822:6"/>forth his Fables in the Schools, which being compoſed with ſuch incomparable and acute Wit, Jeaſt and Merriment, that each Schollar daily ſtrove who ſhould outvie the other in the Diſpute and Rehearſal of them.</p>
            <p>To declare any further of what this little Piece do mention and concern, I need not, leſt I ſhould be found faulty in the too much praiſe of it, or at leaſt too tedious to the Reader; for I my ſelf do love matters in brief, and not of too long feigned circumſtance: Therefore I deſire thee, Reader, as I have taken the pains in Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, ſo do thou ſpend thy labour in Reading it; and I'le give thee
<pb facs="tcp:55822:6"/>leave to ſpend thy Verdict. If it be worthy of thy approbation, and found acceptable to thy Fancy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Author but Thanks, who did endeavour ſo willingly to ſerve thee in this:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And he will remain thy Friend, if deſerv'd. Tho. Howard.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>But take this Verſe with thee.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>TO learn to live, to read, to know,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou art commanded to:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To live, to learn, to know, to read,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All theſe things thou muſt do.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:7"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then learn to read, and read to know,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If thou wouldſt learn to live:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And read to learn what I have writ,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>which will not thee deceive.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:7"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY Of the Seven Wiſe Miſtriſſes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ometime in <hi>Rome</hi> there li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a goodly and renowned Empreſs, named <hi>Lucreſius,</hi> a Lady of great Vertue and marvellous Wiſdome: ſhe was ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heireſs born to the Emperial Crown, and eſpouſed the Son of a King, who was a rich and glorious Prince, and honoured above all others, being graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his Empreſs, loving to his Subjects, and amiable to all; She conceived by him, and bare him a Daughter, named <hi>Sabrina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the moſt faireſt in all the world. This <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brina</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:8"/>grew apace moſt beautiful, lovely, and comly, and eſteemed by all the people in that ſame Land, the onely Iewel throughout the whole Empire: and it happened that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſixth year of her age, there was one Province within the King her Fathers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which cauſed many inſurrections, mutinies, and rebellions to be made againſt their Sovereign, which required the King to make the more haſte for ſuppreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, leſt by their rude inducements they ſhould gather together a force too inconſiderable for his ſtrength to reduce; thereupon he beat up hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Drums, pitcht up his Royal Standard, and ſummoned all his Lords and Noble Barrons of his Realm to appear, and with a mighty force haſted away to ſuppreſs the rude multitute which had rebelled; but the weather proving unconſtant and various, and he forced in ſuch full ſpeed, through heat and cold, he chanced by the way to fall ſick of a Feaver, and lying in ſuch a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate condition, without hopes of recovery, he conſidered more the education of his young Daughter, then the ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his whole Empire, in reference to the innocency and weakneſs of her age: and therefore it induced him to write unto his
<pb facs="tcp:55822:8"/>Empreſs this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>Dear Lady, my Journey hath proved very ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful to me, for by the way I am taken ſick with a moſt ſad and grievous Feaver; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray make haſte unto me, that we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the education of our young Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> and the State, and ſettlement of our Empire, for I am without hopes of recovery, and if you make not great ſpeed you are never like to ſee me alive.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The meſſenger poſted away to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and finding her walking in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, expecting every hour news from her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved husband, he did reverence unto her, and delivered the Letter; the Empreſs broke it up, and reading what condition her Lord was in, fell in a ſwound, to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all her Ladies: but as ſoon as ſhe had recovered life, ſhe cauſed her Chariot and Horſes to be made ready incontinent, and halted both night and day till ſhe came to her Lord the King, who ſhe found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead, and ſhe fell upon his breaſt, and kiſſed his clay cold lips, he riſing half up in his bed with ſnowres of fears betwixt each face, he to her ſpake thus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55822:9"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>O my dear Lady, it joyes me that you are come, where with you I may impart all my troubled minde I am poſſeſt withall; ſince I may not eſcape this infirmity: the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral love and care I bear unto you, and your young Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> makes me ſue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you thus: Firſt, that you cauſe her to be brought up with the beſt experienced and wiſeſt Matron in all the Realm, whereby ſhe might be tutored and well educated in all Arts and Sciences, befitting a Princeſs ſo nobly deſcended; and after that ſhe hath attained unto all thoſe Vertues, I will that you take her home to your Royal Palace,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:9"/>and to have recourſe to your honourable Councel, whereby ſhe may perfect her ſelf in all State and Temporal Affairs: And thirdly, that after your deceaſe, ſhe may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Empire, and wear the Royal Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. And you my dear Lady, conſidering you are old add well ſtricken in years, I will that you chuſe by the adviſe of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Councel a wiſe and grave Senator to aſſiſt your Royal perſon in all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the affairs of the Empire, and Guardian to your young Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> till ſhe come to Maturity. The grieved Empreſs anſwered, My dear Lord, all theſe things ſhall be performed, and done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your will and requeſt: then kiſſing each other, the King turned himſelf upon his Pillow, and gave up the ghoſt; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards conveighed into his own Countrey, and his doleful Funeral ſolemnized, he was honourably interred in his own Chappel.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:10"/>
               <head>Chap. 1.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the Empreſs and her Councel committed the charge of her Daughter Sabrina to ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes, for her Education in all Arts and Sciences.</head>
               <p>IT happened upon a time as the Empreſs was ſolitary walking in her Garden, ſhe bethought her ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the death of her late Husband; and muſing in her heart of the words he ſpake unto her at his laſt breath, concerning the State of his Empire, and eſpecially his young Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> whoſe onely delight in all the world ſhe was, muttered in her heart and ſaid, Now my dear Lord and Husband is dead and gone, there is but one in the world whom I take pleaſure in, and that is my onely Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> the dory ſtower and glory of all other Virgins, and but ſhe alive to inherit my Realm after me, it is good whiles ſhe is yong that ſhe be ſet unto ſome wiſe experienced Matron, who is a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly and devout Virgin, to learn underſtanding, and to reſolve Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when time might require her upon the Iudgement Seat. Thereupon the Empreſs aſſembled all the Lords of her Councel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:55822:10"/>her, and demanded every one his advice concerning her young daughter <hi>Sabrina;</hi> and ſome of them gave their advice that the Empreſs ſhould build a Tower within her own C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle, and cauſe to be put in there the young Lady, with fide devout and wiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to attend her, and two Philoſopers which then lived in <hi>Rome,</hi> to inſtruct her in natural Philoſophy, and other arts and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but the other Lords of the Councel would not agrée thereto, and flood up, and ſaid to the Empreſs thus; Moſt Sovereign Lady, this is not expedient that ſhe ſhould be in ſuch a tower, nor in ſuch a way inſtructed, for thrée things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if ſhe be in ſuch a tower, your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Ladies that frequent your Palace, by too often viſiting her, will make her minde more the pleaſures of the Court, then to practice in her learning.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Men tutors are not méet for ſuch a Princeſs ſo incomparable in beauty as ſhe is, for through too much familiarity and weakneſs of her tender years, great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries may enſue, and her Princely Vertues ſtained.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for her Attendants being but five weak Ladies, and conſequently not over
<pb facs="tcp:55822:11"/>skilful, might for hopes of future advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to pleaſe the young Lady, give her too much liberty in yielding to her fancies, and thereby deſtroy the beſt time of her ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>But gracious Lady, there is living not far from this City, in a fair and ſtately Cloiſter, ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes, moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and expert in wiſdom, anſwering all Reaſons and Queſtions, and for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous skill and learning excelleth all women in the world, the Empreſs hearing this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to their advice, and ſent her Letter of Summons unto them, upon great penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to appear before her Majeſty: They anon came, and the Empreſs demanded the cauſe of their coming? they anſwered, we ſhall reſolve you the cauſe, for we have ſeen it in a dream, which was this:</p>
               <p>We ſaw a high and mighty trée, whoſe branches covered all the Realm, under whoſe leaves the beaſts of the earth did ſhelter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number; and in an inſtant we ſawit fall &amp; diſſolve, that nothing but the roots remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed obvious: The Empreſs ſaid, ſhew me the meaning thereof? they ſaid, the trée which we ſaw was our Sovereign Lord the King, the ſproading branches ſignified his power
<pb facs="tcp:55822:11"/>extending over all his Empire; when the trée falling, it ſignified our Lord died, out of whoſe roots is ſprung up a young Cien who ſhall rule the Empire with equity and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whoſe learning and education you will commit to our charge.</p>
               <p>You have ſaid right, anſwered the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, for my Lord is dead, and I have but one onely Daughter in all the world who I commit unto you to inſtruct and conform in all good wayes and vertues learning, ſo that by your skill and wiſdom ſhe may attain to all good things appertaining to ſo great and noble a Patronage, &amp;c.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:12"/>
               <p>The firſt Miſtris named <hi>Halicuja,</hi> ſaid, great Lady, commit the education of your Daughter to me, and I ſhall teach her as much wiſdom Eccleſiaſtical and Civil in ſeven years, as I and all my fellows can all dayes of our lives.</p>
               <p>Then ſtood up the ſecond Miſtris named <hi>Mardula,</hi> and ſaid, Great Lady, I have tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tored Emperors daughters, and inſtructed Quéens both at home and abroad in all arts and ſciences; therefore if you pleaſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver your Daughter to me, I ſhall learn her as much natural Philoſophy in ſix years as I and all my fellows have.</p>
               <p>The third then addreſſed her ſelf, named <hi>Cicre,</hi> and ſaid, gracious Lady, I have been with you in ſtrange Countreyes, and ſhewed you by my Art and Skill in the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets what noble Prince ſhould wed ye, and never asked any reward, onely this, if I may obtain that favour of ye, as to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe me the tuition and inſtruction of your daughter, I will inform her as much in five years as all the Miſtriſſes in <hi>Rome</hi> can.</p>
               <p>The fourth Miſtriſs drew near the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, who was called <hi>Penthiſilia,</hi> and ſaid, Great Lady, I have been Governeſs to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ladies, and have ſerved you in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:12"/>therefore if you will deliver your Daughter to me, I will train her up in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and teach her as perfect in all arts and ſciences in four years as I and all my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows be.</p>
               <p>The fifth Miſtriſs named <hi>Debora,</hi> then addreſſed her ſelf, and ſaid, O honoured La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I have by my ſkill and wiſdom defended the City of <hi>Rome</hi> from dangerous and great invaſions, and many times called to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate houſe, where they have profited much by my counſel: yet the greateſt thing I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in the world, is to have your Daughter to inſtruct, and I will learn her to do as mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous things in three years as I and all my fellow Students.</p>
               <p>Then addreſſed the ſixth, named <hi>Dejanara,</hi> and ſaid, Dread Lady, if you commit the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of your Daughter to me, I will teach her as much as all can do in two years. And likewiſe the ſeventh Miſtriſs ſaid, Glorious Empreſs, vouchſafe your Daughter me, and I will learn her as much art and ſcience in one year as is in all the world.</p>
               <p>Then ſtood up the Empreſs, and ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all, I render unto you many thanks; for as much as I am obliged unto you all, but if I ſhould commit the charge
<pb facs="tcp:55822:13"/>of my onely Daughter to one, and not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for her education, the event would prove a great diſcord amongſt you; therefore do I commit her to the charge of you all joyntly together, to teach and tutor in all learning, vertue, and wiſdom, as beſt fits a Princeſs in ſuch Royal dignity.</p>
               <p>The wiſe and learned Miſtriſſes hearing the noble and generous expreſſion of the Empreſs, knowing it to be but juſtice, with a full and general accord they agreed together, and with great joy returned thanks to the Empreſs, ſo received her Daughter, and led her away towards a ſumptuous Pallace ſome four miles out of <hi>Rome;</hi> and going on their way, <hi>Baodicia</hi> ſaid to her fellows, if we ſhould now inſtruct and teach this childe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and grant her recourſe to the pleaſant Gardens, it would prove a hinderance to her princely ſtudy: Moreover, the Egyptian Knights hearing of ſo great a beauty, might by chance, when we little think of it, ſteal her away by force. Then anſwered <hi>Mardula,</hi> Let us put her in the brazen tower, on which are ſeven locks, and let every one of us keep a key, and we will paint upon all Inſtruments of Muſick, <hi>The ſeven liberal Sciences,</hi> that when ever ſhe delights to play
<pb facs="tcp:55822:13"/>upon the Muſick, ſhe might there behold her Doctrine thereon, ſo that it may never be out of memory.</p>
               <p>This ſaying pleaſed all well, and being done accordingly, the Miſtriſſes uſed their beſt skill and diligence in attending the young Lady, for the ſpace of ſeven years; which being expired, they appointed a day for to prove her experience, in what ſhe had learnt; thereupon they all conſented, and for the trial thereof propoſed three queſtions to her.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what number of ſtars were fixed in the Firmament?</p>
               <p>She anſwered, that number firſt created.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when do the Planets begin to riſe?</p>
               <p>She anſwered, after they go down.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what knowledge made women wiſeſt?</p>
               <p>She anſwered, the knowledge of good and evil.</p>
               <p>The wiſe Miſtriſſes hearing theſe wiſe and accute anſwers, ſaid among themſelves, doubtleſs this Lady will be a famous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and alſo will excel all her Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:14"/>
               <head>Chap. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the Empreſs by the advice of her Lords, choſe Radamentus her aſſiſtant in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Empire, and alſo Guardian to her Daughter Sabrina.</head>
               <p>NOw about this time the Princes of the Land, with all the Barons, aſſembled themſelves together before the Empreſs in full Councel, for the election of a grand Conſul, expert in the Laws and cuſtoms of the Empire, for to aſſiſt the Empreſs in all Temporal Affairs, according to the will of her late Husband the King; and they choſe one <hi>Radamentus,</hi> who was Vncle to the late King, a wiſe and cunning Politick, and one whom the Empreſs repoſed great confidence in; that whatſoever he did enact or contrive ſhe was ready to ſign: to which the Nobles of the Land gave their general conſent, for the better eaſe of the Queen, and their own future trouble. This <hi>Radamentus</hi> helding the Helm of the Empire in ſo great ſway, he grew haughty and ambitious to more honour, and thinking to himſelf, that the Empreſs was weak and ſickly, and if ſhe did dye, 'twas probable he may take the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:14"/>ſole Government to himſelf, and rule as Lord and Emperour.</p>
               <p>But underſtanding the Empreſs had a young Daughter, and brought up in the School of <hi>the ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes,</hi> and right heir to the Crown; he thought when ſhe came to maturity ſhe would out-wit him, and prove more craftier then himſelf: therefore from that time he daily ſought her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now there was a Law at that time, that whoſoever was found in Fornication or Adultery, were to dye by that Law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy; ſo upon a day, as the Empreſs and <hi>Radamentus</hi> were both walking in the Garden, <hi>Radamentus</hi> ſeemed to be very melancholly, and would not ſpeak: the Empreſs ſéeing him ſo heavy, marvelled greatly, and asked him the cauſe of his ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: who anſwered, Now the Realm is in full peace and quietneſs, there is but one thing I requeſt of you; the Empreſs ſaid, Ask what you will, it ſhall be granted to the one half of my Prerogative.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the Conſul, you have but one onely Daughter in the world, and heireſs to the Empire, and ſhe you cauſe to be detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between ſtone walls, wherein ſhe ſpends the flower of her years onely in thoughts and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:15"/>contemplations, that what ſhe (as a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs) do there imagine within, the varieſt wretch in the world do ſee it actually abroad; therefore ſand for her to Court, that you may have conſolation of her, and ſhe may ſee the practice thereof, and have recourſe to the Councel. Then anſwexed the Empreſs, I like your ſaying, for it is ſeven years ſince I have ſeen her; thereupon ſhe wrote Letters ſigned with her privy Signet and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to <hi>the ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes,</hi> for to haſten away to the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> again ſuch a day, and bring <hi>Sabrina</hi> the young Princeſs with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes, after ſight of the Empreſs Letters, by their powerful skill went to ſearch the Planets; by which they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Deſign of Radamentus.</head>
               <p>WHen the Miſtriſſes had received the Empreſs Letter, and underſtood the Contents thereof, they fell to their books, and fathomed their skill, directing their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and marking the Planets, if the cauſe of their going might be fortunate or no. And they found a great contageon among
<pb facs="tcp:55822:15"/>
                  <figure/> the ſignes from whence they did predict that when they preſented the young Lady, if ſhe ſhould anſwer any more words then one, her enemies would have power over her to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray her to the ſhamefulleſt death that may be; ſo they were very heavy, and mourned all the day lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: about the evening tide, came down the young Lady <hi>Sabrina,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light her ſelf upon the Muſick, and ſeeing all the ſeven Miſtriſſes very ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, ſhe deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the cauſe of their grief; who anſwere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, O Lady, this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rning we have received Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the Empreſs, that we forthwith to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſte to Court, and bring you along with us,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:16"/>and we have ſeen a Star that your journey will prove fatal if you ſpeak any more words then one, which is <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that you ſhall ſay and no more for the ſpace of ſeven dayes; and this is the thing which grieves us, that ſince we have nouriſhed you for ſo many years, ſhould now at the laſt be reduced to ſuch a hazard.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the young Lady, being full of vertuous learning, I have viewed the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament my ſelf, and marked the motions of the leſſer Stars, and found your ſaying true; but if you will hear my counſel, and receive my advice, without doubt my vertue ſhall overtop their vice, and my cunning wiſdom ſhall excéed their crafty treachery: Then ſaid the Miſtriſſes, ſpeak on your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, we will hearken to it; and ſhe ſaid, I ſhall be accus'd of an evil perſon, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly condemned: but if every of you ſeven can ſpeak to my mother the Empreſs, each one her day for ſeven dayes together in my behalf, I ſhall eſcape my life: the Miſtriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hearing this, they all accorded in a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful harmony, and ſaid among themſelves, what joy is come to us, ſurely ſhe will be an Empreſs of great fame and wiſdom: ſo they cloathed her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cloth of gold and rich orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:16"/>and provided a Chariot of Azure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, drawn by four white Stéeds, who gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pac'c the ground like as they trod by ſome directed ſteps in the air; ſo with a train of pure Virgins ſhe was accompanied to the Empreſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the Empreſs hearing her Daughter was coming on the way, rode in great triumph with all her Princes and Barons to meet her.</head>
               <p>WHen the Empreſs heard that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven wiſe Miſtriſſes of <hi>Rome</hi> were coming with her young Daughter <hi>Sabrina,</hi> ſhe cauſed all her Chariots to be made ready, and with her Heraulds, Trophies, and Banners, accompanied with all her Nobles, rode on the way to meet them: but ſaid the Miſtriſſes to <hi>Sabrina,</hi> it were good for us to depart and go into the City ſome other way, and diligently watch the Planets in their ſeveral motions, for the ſafeguard of your life, and the preſervation of us; to this the young Lady willingly condeſcended, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me in my neceſſity, ſhe ſaid: ſo they departed, and the young Lady rode on her
<pb facs="tcp:55822:17"/>
                  <figure/> way: but when the Empreſs ſaw her, ſhe took her in her arms and kiſſed her, ſaying, O my dear Daughter, the onely delight I have in the world, whom God doth preſerve for future bleſſings, how is it with you? now I hope you will be to me the flower of my external happineſs, being conformed in all vertues learning, the fitter to ſit upon my Iudgement Seat after me: the young Lady bowed and did reverence unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, but ſpake not a word. When the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſaw this, for bluſhed with very fear, ſome evil had befallen her, that ſhe ſpak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and yet ſhe thought in her ſelf, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:55822:17"/>out of the Countrey ſo many years, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrange Arts ſhe might forget her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral language, and a thouſand other things came in her minde: And anon ſhe asked her again, what ſhe had learnt ſo many years with the wiſe Miſtriſſes of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſo bowed her ſelf, and ſpake not one word more. Then the Empreſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her Lords how and in what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition her daughter was in, and ſaid, for the evil the Miſtriſſes had wrought with her, they ſhould dye the moſt ſhameful death that could be thought of; and when ſhe came to the Palace, ſhe took her by the hand and led her into the great Hall, out of thence into the Garden, and plac'd her by her in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour upon her own ſeat, and ſaid, My good Daughter, declare unto me the reaſon by ſome certain ſign why you will not ſpeak, or elſe here is a pen and paper, write to me your minde; ſhe took the pen in her hand and wrote theſe lines.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Through Learning which doth me adorn,</l>
                  <l>I very plainly ſee,</l>
                  <l>The Star where under I was born</l>
                  <l>proves fatal now to me:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:18"/>
                  <l>And I in bed have lately dream'd,</l>
                  <l>what after will enſue;</l>
                  <l>That I three times ſhall be condemn'd</l>
                  <l>in Judgement-ſeat by you.</l>
               </q>
               <p>When the Empreſs ſaw theſe lines, ſhe was aſtoniſht and wondered greatly, for ſhe knew not the meaning thereof, how that ſhe ſhould give Iudgement thrée times on her own Daughter, ſhe wrung her hands, and mourned greatly; then came <hi>Radamentus</hi> the great Conſul, and ſaid unto the Empreſs, is this your Daughter which hath béen brought up with the ſeven wiſe Miſtriſſes of <hi>Rome?</hi> the Empreſs anſwered, this is my Daughter and onely Heir to the Empire, but ſhe now has no expreſſion with her tongue: <hi>Rada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentus</hi> ſtood ſtill and beheld her, and ſaw her countenance ſo pleaſant, and of ſuch incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable beauty, that the like was not in all the world, he burned inwardly with luſt, and deceitfully ſaid to the Empreſs, deliver her to me, and by often perſwaſion without doubt Ile make her declare to me her whole ſtudience; this did he not onely for love and honour he bore to her, but rather to ſatisfie his inſatiate luſtful appetite, and after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire her deſtruction, which was the main
<pb facs="tcp:55822:18"/>thing ho aimed at, but God infuſed in the heart of the Princeſs not to go with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">How Radamentus watched his opportunity how he might ſurprize the Princeſs in the Garden, and how he conſpired to take away her life.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAdamentus</hi> after this, being in his chamber window, eſpied the Princeſs going into the Garden to walk under the Sickamore-trees, without any body with her, and it happened that ſhe left the key in the door on the inſide and forgot to ſhut it.</p>
               <p>The old Conſul came down and entered the Garden, locking the door, and taking the key out, he came to the Lady upon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as ſhe was contemplating under the tree; who at the preſence of <hi>Radamentus,</hi> ſhe began to bluſh, that there appeared in her face ſuch a Crimſon dye, that the malice of <hi>Radamentus</hi> was reduced into a venial love: and thus he began to court her.</p>
               <p>Gentle Lady, give me leave to tell ye, that the firſt time I ſaw ye, there was a fire kindled within my heart, and now your beauty begets another, which nothing can
<pb facs="tcp:55822:19"/>alay, except you vouchſafe me the favour to let me ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p with you upon this bed of Roſes, and repoſe our ſelves in the boſom of love: the Royal Princeſs turned about, and with a ſcornful geſture gave a repulſe to his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious demand, which cauſed his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to fall, and his fancy turned to fury; therefore he ran out of the Garden, and lockt the door, and threw the key in again, and cryed out, that he ſaw the Princeſs with a man under a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g-tree, committing the foul ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Fornication, as a breach of the Law, the ſhame of her Parents, and the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of her own ſoul. The Empreſs hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, was ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ck with horrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, to think that her onely daughter and heir to the Empire ſhould prove ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unate: Firſt, inſtead of Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, ſhe ſhould have been perfected with, ſhe was delivered unto me ſpeechleſs; where I thought ſhe was adorned with vertues, ſhe is beſotted with vice; I would the day of her birth had been the day of her burial: ſo the Empreſs believed all that the wicked Conſul had reported, and the Nobles that were preſent asked where he ſaw her, and he ſaid, under a Sickamore-tree, but ſaid, the man when he perceived me, ran away, then
<pb facs="tcp:55822:19"/>the Nobles haſted into the Garden, and found the Princeſs walking by her ſelf, they ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her what man had been with her there: ſhe anſwered nothing. Then the Empreſs ſeeing it apparent that ſhe was in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as <hi>Radamentus</hi> reported, believed all as was ſaid; therefore in rage and choller ſhe commanded her to be led away and burnt at a ſtake: but the Ladies which came with the Princeſs and other of the Nobility, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed themſelves to the Empreſs, and ſaid, Gracious Lady, ſhe is your onely Daughter, and all you have in the world, it is good, that ſhe have a little reſpite, and you better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the maſter, it may chance to prove but a miſtake of the Conſul; for if you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily thus put her to death, it will accrew to your diſhonour, and we ſhall gain reproach of all Nations; therefore let a day be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and ſhe appear in judgement, if ſhe deſerve death to be found by twelve men, and fairly condemned by the Law. At this the Empreſs bethought her ſelf, being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reconciled of her raſhneſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted her to ſafe priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:20"/>
               <head>Chap. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">How Radamentus complained againſt the young Princeſs, and how he accuſed her of Fornication, being death by the Law.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAdamentus</hi> finding his accuſation took effect, no time was omitted for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution thereof, for his inſatiable ſpirit would not be ſatisfied till life and all was gone; therefore he came again to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs as a man in great ſorrow and pain: and the Empreſs ſaid, My grave Lord and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour, what aileth you to be ſo heavy? O Lady, ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> how ſhould I other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe chuſe, thinking what ſtain and defama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will rely upon this our Empire, becauſe of your graceleſs Daughter, through her laſcivious actions within your Court, as a common Whore; and if you let her live any longer in this foul ſin, you will be counted no leſs your ſelf, and rendered odious over all the world, for the rumour of people will be upon you, ſaying, what need we fear to break the Law, ſince the law-makers do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it, the Daughter of the Empreſs is both a Whore and a Strumpet; and thus through her means we ſhall have vice ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:20"/>and vertue oppreſſed: for what néed they care, ſince they have ſuch evil prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. Then ſaid the Empreſs, to prevent all theſe evils, to morrow I ſhall ſit in Iudgement, and ſhe ſhall dye by the Law. Then ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> ſee it be ſo done, leſt it happen to you as it did to a Lady in <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia,</hi> of whom an example is mentioned. Relate the example, ſaid the Empreſs, I ſhall incontinent, ſaid <hi>Radamentus.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The firſt Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>In Capadocia was a Lady who kept a ſumptuous Garden, in which was one of the vertuouſeſt Wells in the world, that whoſoever ſhould be bit with any venomous beaſt; waſh but in that water, they were immediately cured.</p>
                  <p>It happened on a day as the Lady was walking in her Garden a gathering of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſhe eſpied in a corner of the Garden in the ſide of a little Rock, a ſmall prill of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter running fair and criſtal, abundant more clear then the vertuous wel was, which cauſed her to imagine, that if the Rock were carved, there would iſſue a water more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the well-water, and ſaid unto the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:21"/>Gardiner, get me a workman that he may hew this Rock, whereby I may have a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Fountain here; and I give you charge over it, and to ſee it done. The Gardiner anſwered, your will ſhall be fulfilled. But another time the Lady came into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and viewed the little Spring; but it appeared not ſo ſtrong in running as ſhe thought it would: and ſhe ſaid, wherefore runs it not bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er? her man ſaid, the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſpring was deep in the earth, and had two wayes, the one to the Weil, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Rock; but that to the Well is greater, and by its ſtrength draws more wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the well; and therefore its ſtream is ſo little. Then ſaid the Lady, deſtroy the well then, for queſtionleſs this ſpring will prove the better water; ſo the Gardener dam'd up the vertuous water, that there was no more ſeen. And another day the Lady came again into the Garden to ſée her yong Spring, and taſte the water, and it proved very ſad and bitter; and having its courſe through a tin mine, whatſoever ſick perſon did bathe in it, it would putrifie their ſore, and augment their pain; ſo that all people did curſe the Counſellours that did adviſe the Lady to deſtroy the vertuous well.
<pb facs="tcp:55822:21"/>Then ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> underſtand you great Lady what I have ſaid? yes, right well ſaid the Empreſs, then ſaid he, I will ſhew you the meaning thereof.</p>
                  <div type="lesson">
                     <head>The Declaration of the Example.</head>
                     <p>The vertuous Well, great Lady, be token<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your ſelf, and how that with your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and wiſe Iudgements you govern the people with equity, that whoſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth to you ſhould have Iuſtice and their ſick caſes mitigated; and the young Spring ſo fair and criſtal, is your graceleſs luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Daughter, who will cauſe your Royal name to be blaſted, and your vertuous Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment deſpiſed, whoſe actions are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, running through a tin mine, that is, ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e and inferiour carrages, not in Royalty of a Princely parentage; ſo that quickly ſhe will break your heart, and reign after you, then all people will curſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours that adviſed you to let her live: therefore great Lady I counſel you while it is time, to cut her off and deſtroy her, leſt the curſe of the Empire follow you. Then ſaid the Empreſs, all that ſhall not happen, for to morrow I ſhall ſit in Iudgement, and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:22"/>ſhe ſhall dye without fail. When the day was come, the Empreſs ſate in Iudgement, and commanded her Officers to lead her away to be burnt at a ſtake, and as we was led through the City in a long ſmock of Lawn and a branch of Roſemary in her hand, and the Trumpets ſounding her dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Funeral, all the people ran out and wept, crying, alas, alas, the onely Daughter of the Empreſs is leading to death. Then came <hi>Debora</hi> the firſt Miſtris paſſing by, as the young Lady ſaw her, ſhe bowed der head, as if ſhe ſaid, remember me when you come before my Mother; and when ſhe came to the Empreſs, and did reverence, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſaid unto her with a ſtorn counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Thou ungrateful and vile woman, how haſt thou tutozed my childs, I deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to thee well and hopeful, and now ſhe is become the viceouſeſt creature that ever a woman bare, ſurely thou ſhalt dye as ſtrange a death as may be thought on. Then ſaid the Miſtris, gracious Lady, the cauſe why ſhe ſpeaketh not, the divine powers know, and without cauſe it is not; and as for the ſin of Fornication, we all can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that for the ſpace of theſe ſeven years, we never ſaw the leaſt motion, neither in
<pb facs="tcp:55822:22"/>thought, word, nor déed; therefore gracious Lady, if you do put her to death, onely for the accuſation of <hi>Radamentus,</hi> it will happen to you as it did unto the Queen of <hi>Syra,</hi> who poiſoned her huſband through the perſwaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one wicked perſon. Then ſaid the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſhew me that example? Nay, ſaid the Miſtris, except you ſend for your Daughter back, otherwiſe, ſhe may be dead before I make an end, then will it be in vain: upon which words the Empreſs ſent for her Daughter again, and committed her to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; then the Miſtris began as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the firſt Miſtriſs.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>Syra</hi> lived a Quéen of great renown, and of ſuch excellent beauty, that a fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er woman was not in all the world, for which many Kings and Princes of Noble Blood came a ſuiting to her, each man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident ſhe ſhould be his: This Queen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted much in ſeeing Iuſts and Turneys; therefore it was a day appointed, and they all aſſembled together to ſhew their valour before the Quéen; amongst whom was <hi>Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> a moſt valiant Prince, and of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable features and beauty, that his
<pb facs="tcp:55822:23"/>like was not among men. Vpon this Prince the Queen fixed her eye all that part of the day; in whoſe ſight he did ſuch worthy acts, that deſerved perpetual memory: and to be brief, he had the day of all the Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Barons that were there; whereby he came off the Field with Trumpets ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and victorious Trophies bore before him. On the morrow after the Queen ſent for him, and when be came he kneeled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her to have kiſt her hand, but ſhe refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and in a comely deportment tendered her lips: The Prince being ſomewhat baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the Queen gave him farther encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that by little and little they grew in a wonderful familiarity; and ſoon after the Queen took him for her Husband, and made him joynt King of <hi>Syra</hi> with her. He was a wiſe and gracious Prince, and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all his Subjects, all people joyed at his preſence, the whole land ſorrowed in his abſence; never no Queen loved King bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor never was Queen more beloved of a King: and it came to paſs afterwards, that the King of the <hi>Parthians</hi> lay very ſick, whoſe Son this King was, and he received a Letter from his Father to make haſte un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that after his death he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uld take
<pb facs="tcp:55822:23"/>poſſeſſion of the Realm; and after a while he was gone, an evil Counſellour in his Court being in love with the Queen, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted all the Kings Letters that paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen him and his Queen, and informed the Quéen he had married another Lady in his own Countrey; which raiſed ſuch jealouſis in the Quéen, that ſhe tore the ornaments of her head, wringing her hands, ſaying, O my dear Lord, what evil have I done, what word have I miſpla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, wherein have I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended you, that another ſhould reap the Conſolation of your Love! The King in the mean time wondering be could never receive any Letter from the Queen, lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, O my Dear, wherein have I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended I can never hear how you do, nor how the affairs of our Kingdom ſtandeth! All this while the wicked Counſellor intercept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Letters on both ſides to work the deſtruction of the King; and at laſt he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented a ſtrong Perſon, and carried the ſame to the Queen, and told her it was of ſuch a Vertue, that if the would cauſe a King to be made hollow, and put a little of this vertue in it, and ſond it to the King as a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and as oft as ever the King old lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> upon it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>would cauſe him to forſake all
<pb facs="tcp:55822:24"/>other women and haſte home unto her: ſo the Quéen believed his wicked counſel, and was very glad, and without the advice of any other ſhe cauſed a King to be made as he had ſaid, and put therein this poiſon, and ſent it away to her Husband: When the meſſenger came before him, he did him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and preſented the King to him; the harmleſs King joyfully put it on, ſaying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>was the ſwéeteſt preſent he ever received: ſoon after his finger began to ſwell, and he ſent for his Phyſicians, who ſaid his finger was venomed with the ſtrongeſt poyſon in the world, and ſaid he muſt cut it off, elſe 'twould venome his whole body: Then ſaid the King cut it off, which accordingly was done; then his arm began to ſwell, and in like manner that was cut off to preſerve his life: Then the good King groaned out this complaint, O thou vile woman, why haſt thou done this to him who thou wert as dear to as his own ſoul, thou haſt attempted that by poyſon which the ſtouteſt Champion durſt not do by arms; I that hath won thée the greateſt glory that ever came to <hi>Syra,</hi> haſt thou now deſtroyed with inferiour poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for which thou wilt gain reproach of all Nations, and be reviled of all women, for
<pb facs="tcp:55822:24"/>returning me malicious poyſon for pure in flamed love; but all as I can ſay is, ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is the grandeſt inſolency in the world, O woman why haſt thou done this? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſunk down in his Chair, and gave up the ghoſt. The meſſenger haſted home, and told the Queen what had happened by the King, and that all the Counſellor had fold her of the King was falſe: then the Quéen fell a wéeping and wringing her hands, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O what hade I done, what have I done? I have by the advice of an evil Counſellor ſlain my dear Husband the King! O curſed Traytor, would to God I had ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e receiv'd thy wicked counſel; but ſince I embraced thy helliſh advice, with this hand that firſt handled the curſed King I will be revenged on my ſelf, and ſo took a knife and thruſt it into her breaſt, and ſo ended her life. Then ſaid the Miſtris to the Empreſs, underſtand you what I have ſaid? Yes, right well ſaid the Empreſs, you have ſhew'd me a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; without doubt this day my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall not dye: Then ſaid the Miſtris, if you do ſo, you will do wiſely, and I thank you for ſparing your Daughters life this day for my ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:25"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Complaint of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>When <hi>Radamentus</hi> underſtood the Princeſs had obtain'd Pardon through the means of <hi>Hallicuja</hi> the wiſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, he retired to his Chamber, and ſeemed to grieve and lament extraordinary; but alas it was nothing but falſhood and deceit; ſo that he refuſed to come to Councel: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the Empreſs was much troubled, and thereupon ſent for him and demanded the cauſe of his grief, and the reaſon wherefore he did not attend to Councel? who anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Great Lady, what greater pain can there be to a man, then when he is reviled of every vulgar tongue undeſervedly; for all people know I am you aſſiſtant in the Empire, and think I am at the helm of Iuſtice, where I do rather more ſupport wickedneſs then equity, and maintain vice where I ſhould tertue; ſince of late there hath béen whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and debauchery committed in the very Court, and the Empreſs own Daughter did it: what ſcandal is this that I ſhall lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, beſide your Royal Perſon will be defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the honour of your Kingdom the object of the world; for you abſtain Iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:55822:25"/>from being executed upon that vile wretch your curſed Daughter, ſo that ſhe liveth to the ruine of the Empire: therefore it ſhall happen to you as it did to the Quéen of <hi>Pirus</hi> and her daughter. The Empreſs ſaid, I pray you ſhew me that Example: why, ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> let me ſhew you never ſo many, it availeth not; nevertheleſs I will ſhew you this, which is as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The ſecond Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>IN <hi>Pirus</hi> reigned a vertuous Quéen, her Husband being dead, ſhe had one onely Daughter, whom ſhe tendered above her life; this Daughter grew apace crafty and cunning, and often converſed with Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, to whom ſhe complained there was but one Nobleman which hindered her from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her will and liberty: ſaid the Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, Ile teach you a way to betray his life, and then you may do well enough with your mother. Pray ſhew me that way ſaid ſhe, that I will ſaid the Sorcerer, that is this: When he is walking in the Garden, go you to him, and if he ſit down, ſit you by him, 'twill be a provocation to move his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and as he doth precéed, then give him
<pb facs="tcp:55822:26"/>incouragement; if he refuſe you, cry out, he has raviſht you: So this impudent wretch ſate by this Nobleman, and ſmiled upon him and ſmute him with the palm of her hand upon the chéek, and ſaid, come let us ſolace our ſelves in the boſom of love until the dark Evening: Then ſaid the Lord, Great Lady, excuſe me, for I am not furniſht with ſo much conſidence as to deflower the Pearls of our Land. At which words this Lady tore her locks down about her ſhoulders, and cryed out, alas, alas, what ſhall I do! The Quéen her Mother being in the Window heard the cry, and looking out, eſpied her Daughter in the Garden crying and wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her hands; ſhe ſent down her Lords to know the matter; and ſhe ſaid, this man, meaning the harmleſs Lord, hath conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me by force under yonder trée, and he hath deſt wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d me of my Virginity: The Quéen hearing this ſaid, ſurely he ſhall dye: Then ſaid the Lords, it is good that you hear him before you put him to death: Nay, ſaid the Quéen, I have heard my daughter, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> further witneſs, I will believe her teſtimony above all the worlds; and thereupon commanded the Lord to be led away and put to death, which accordingly
<pb facs="tcp:55822:26"/>was done. This Lord was the uprighteſt man and greateſt Counſellor the Quéen had; from this time forth ſhe alwayes ſought the deſtruction of her mother: and thus ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, Great Princeſs and Mother, through my obedience and diligent care I bear to you, I would wiſh you to ſpeak not unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mean ſubject when they come for juſtice, but that I between you and them may deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their meſſage, for too much familiarity will breed contempt; therefore the Queen repoſing ſo much confidence in her daughter, thought all for good whatſoever ſhe did do; and thereupon ſet forth a Proclamation, that all perſons whatſoever having buſineſs at the Court, ſhould addreſs themſelves to her Daughter; who alwayes ſitting in an outward Chamber, as people came to her, ſhe ſeemed very milde, amiable and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo through her cunning and diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all people took affections to her, and ſhe would ſay to them, my mother is very raſh being ancient; but if you will take me for your Sovereign, Ile do you juſtice accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the due adminiſtration of the law: at which words they were all very joyful, and promiſed faithfully to perform it, but ſaid ſhe, raiſe your army, ſtand in your own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:27"/>and plead your Subſidies and heavy burthens ate too weighty for you to bear; this do till you hear from me: ſo the rude multitude did as this Imp had advis'd them. Then away ſhe went to her mother, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inted her there was a factious people had rebell'd, and it were good to prevent them in time leaſt they ſhould grow too populous; ſo the Queen gave her the ſupream Authority, in granting Commiſſions to raiſe an Army; ſo when ſhe had got the Seal, ſhe told her mother ſhe muſt have a great quantity of Gold to pay them: Then the Queen deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered two hundred thouſand marks of Gold, and having got this money, ſhe haſted with it all away to her factious Crew; and there paid then: all with her mothers own Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and gave them Commiſſions under her own Seal, that all the reſt of the Subjects were in a maze; for ſeeing their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the Quéens Seal all lay ſtill, and not one moved for the Quéen, thinking it had béen no Rebellion: At laſt this new Army advanced towards the Court, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, this wicked Wretch the Quéens Daughter, haſted to her mother, and told her, that ſhe by her fair ſpéeches had aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the fury of the people, and brought them
<pb facs="tcp:55822:27"/>there to beg their pardon, which ſhe deſired the Quéen to grant them; which being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes betrayed through her ſubtle words, condeſcended; and as ſhe was going out to ſign their Pardons, and conducted by her daughter, ſhe paſſed over a boarded Alloy, where underneath was a Room and Cauldron of boyling Oyl, that this wicked Daughter had provided, with a board wheron her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was to tread; tilting up, the Quéen ſell in, and thereby was deſtroy'd: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was this wicked Wretch proclaimed Quéen, that through laſcivious living and cruel Tyranny all Nations ſpighted her, and her own ſubjects hated her, that as ſhe was coming through the City of <hi>Conbro,</hi> a Butchers man daſht out her brains with his Cleaver: The end of a Tyrant.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Radamentus</hi> ſaid to the Empreſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ye what I have ſaid? and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſe ſaid right well, you have ſhew'd me a good Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mple; therefore to prevent theſe Evils that they ſhall not happen to me, this day my Daughter ſhall dye: And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time ſhe ſate in Indgement, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded bar Daughter to be led away to the place of Execution; and as ſhe was going, the ſecond Miſtries addreſſed her ſelf to the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:28"/>Empreſs, doing her reverence, and ſaid, O great Lady, if you will thus ſlay your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the words of <hi>Radamentus,</hi> if ſhall happen worſe to you then it did to the Lady of <hi>Barbra</hi> and her Lyon. The Empreſs ſaid good Miſtris ſhew me that Example, O great Lady, I ſhall not do it, except you call your Daughter back again until it be told, and if it does not turn your minde, your will be fulfilled afterwards.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the ſecond Miſtriſs.</head>
                  <p>UPon a time there was a Lady and her Husband which deſigned a long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age by Sea, but the winde and weather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving contrary, they were driven to great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and conſtrained to lye a tedious while at ſea, inſomuch that all their proviſion was ſpent; then they continued a whole fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night without any kinde of food, and when nature could not ſubſiſt no longer, they threw dice for their lives who ſhould be kill'd firſt, to make meat for his Fellows, ſo they eat one another in order as they began, until all were eat; ſo this poor Lady and her Husband with force of nature and pure love hindred from killing each other: Then they
<pb facs="tcp:55822:28"/>reſolv'd to dye together, and ſo ſowed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in one Carpet, and laid them down upon the Deck, ſaying, the great God of heaven and earth holy them, and by that time they were full'd eſléep by the rocking of the waves, there chanced to come upon the Deck a great Griffin, that's hall an Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and half a Lyon, ſo that 'tis neither bird nor beaſt, but a Creature as ſtrong as a Horſe, and took up the Carpet in her claws with the Lady and her Husband as a prey for her young ones, and carried them in to a ſtrange Iſland, inhabited with Lyons, Bears, Wolves, and ſuch like Beaſts: When the Griffin had brought them into his neſt, he and his young began to peck at the Carpet, with which they awaked the Lady and her Husband, who being a ſtout Hero opened the Carpet, and eſpied Land; and having his ſword with him, came out and fought a deſperate fight with the Grif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, and ſlaw him and all his young. How to get off this Iſland they did not know, but in wandering up and down the man dyed, and then the poor Lady was alone, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by none but God above; ſo wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Wilderneſs ſhe chanced to meet a mighty he Lyon, whoſe roaring
<pb facs="tcp:55822:29"/>ſéem'd to her like claps of thunder: then when ſhe ſaw him ſhe fell to the ground, ſaying, O greet Ichovah, who holdeth the power of all creatures in thy hands, have mercy upon me. So ſhe drew near unto him, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered that he halted, and the Lion groaned towards her, as thought to have ſome help: ſo ſhe ventered to him, and took up his foot, and therein was a great thorn; and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on patiently holding up his foot, ſhe drew it out; which having done, the Lion fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon her, and lickt her, and in his nature ſhewed as great love and kindneſs to her as ever humans nature could: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he led her to his Den, where ſhe continued for a long ſeaſon, feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nothing but what preys the Lion had brought her, and which may ſoever ſhe walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Lion would attend upon her, and preſerve her from all other ſavage Beaſts. At laſt as ſhe was mourning to her ſelf, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring her condition in living in ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity in a forreign Countrey, whoſe daily companion was but a ſavage Beaſt, her minde yening after her own habitation, ſhe thus complained, O how hath fortune frowned on me, that I am driven out from among all humane knowledge, and am glad
<pb facs="tcp:55822:29"/>to take my living with the Beaſt of the Field. As ſhe thus complained to her ſelf, the Devil chanced to appear unto her, and demanded the cauſe of her complaint, who told him all as you have heard. Then ſaid be to her, What wilt thou give and Ile pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a Ship ſhall carry thee home to thy own Countrey? ſhe anſwered, half her Eſtate. Nay, ſaid the Devil, if thou wilt give me thy ſoul at the tearm of twelve years, I'le ſet thée in thy own Countrey, and then ſhalt live and flouriſh ſo long? God forbid, ſaid the Lady, I'le firſt end my wretched life in this ſolitary Iſland. Why then, ſaid the Devil, I'le make this bargain with ye, that if you can abſtain from ſleeping all the time of our Voyage, which ſhall be but three dayes, I'le have nothing to do with your ſoul, if you ſléep I'le hade it, as I have ſaid: and upon this bargain the Lady ventered, provided ſhe might have her Lion with her; ſo 'twas concluded, and a brave ſhip came and took in the Lady and her Lion: when ſhe lay down the Lion lay by her, and if ſhe ſlumbered, the Lion trould touch her with his paw; by which means he kept her awake all the Voyage, until ſhe landed in her own Countrey; and being come to her Fathers
<pb facs="tcp:55822:30"/>houſe, ſhe knocked at the Gate; then the Porter coming with all ſpéed, opened the Gate, and ſaw it was a Beggar, frowningly he ſhut it again, ſaying, Here's nothing for you: then ſhe bounced at the Gate again, and asked the Porter if ſuch a Knight li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there, meantng her Father, and he ſaid, yes; then ſaid ſhe, pray deliver this piece of King unto him. Now this King was it ſhe brake betwixt her Father and ſhe, at her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of the Land: then the Porter delivered the King to his Maſter, ſaying, The Begger woman at the Gate willed me to deliver this piece of King unto you. When the Knight ſaw the King he fell down in a ſwound, but when he was revived be ſaid, call her in, for ſhe is my onely Daughter, whom I thought was dead. Then ſaid the Porter, I dare not call her in, for there is a mighty he-Lion with her, though it be, ſaid the Knight, call her in, then ſaid the Porter, you are to come in; but leave your Lion out: no, ſaid the Lady, my Lion walketh where I go, and where he is not, there will I not be; and when ſhe came to her father, ſhe fell down on her knées and wept: her father took her up in his arms and kiſt her, weeping as faſt, and after he
<pb facs="tcp:55822:30"/>clothed her in Purple, and plac'd her by him in a chair, and demanded the relation of her Travels, who declared unto him all that happened, and how the Lion had ſaved her life, and was the greateſt comfort ſhe had in the Wilderneſs. It chanced after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that as the Knight was going into his Wood to view his young Horſes, he met with a wilde Boar, with whom he fell in combat with. The Lion loved the old Knight, and by accident walking under the pale ſide, he ſented the Boar, and as the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ran towards the place where the Boar was, the Steward eſpied him, and he ran in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Palace, and cryed out, the Lion is running after my Maſter to deſtroy him. Then the Lady ſent after him ten of her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants who met the Lion with his mouth all bloody, and they ran back and told the Lady the Lion had deſtroyad her aged Father. Then ſaid the Lady, O woe is me that ever I was born, that have brought a Lion from far to deſtroy my own Father; therefore ſhe commanded her ſervants to ſlay the Lion, which no ſooner was done but her Father come in, and ſaid, O I have met with a wilde Boar, with whom I ſought, and there came in the Lion to my aid, and ſlew the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:31"/>Boar, ſo ſaved my life, elſe I had dyed by the Boar. When the Lady heard this, O how ſhe wept and wrung her hands, ſaying, For the words of a wicked Steward, I have ſlain my good Lion, who have ſaved both my life and my Fathers, curſed be the time I was adviſed by him.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Miſtriſs, underſtand you what I have ſaid? yes, right well, ſaid the Empreſs, you have ſhewed me a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a bad adviſe, which cauſed the Lady to ſlay ſo good a Lion, ſurely I'le beware ſuch bad advice, my Daughter ſhall not dye this day. The Miſtris ſaid, if you do ſo you will do well, therefore I commit you to God, and ſtand obliged to your grace for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your-Daughter this day for my ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The third Complaint of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>WHen <hi>Radamentus</hi> perceived the young Princeſs was not dead, he kept his Chamber, and tore his hair, grieving very much, and ſaying, the State of the Empire lies groaning under the ſcandal of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and reputed as the very froth and ſcum of baſeneſs; and as he was thus complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his attendants hearing him, went and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:31"/>imparted it to the Empreſs, and ſhe went to him and asked the cauſe of his lamentation, who anſwered, O great Lady, how can I other wiſe chuſe, knowing ſo great a crime that lyes upon the Empire, through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiſt and laſcivious actions of your grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Daughter, and yet cannot have Iuſtice executed upon her, whereby we may waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſtain that reſts upon your honour &amp; my reputation, the world knowing I am your aſſiſtant in the Government; &amp; ſeeing there is no more reſpect and obſerving of the Laws then there is, I have juſt cauſe to leave your Realm, and ſuffer you to plunge your ſelf in this deluge of ignorance, but that the love I bear to you, and your good Subjects, doth prohibit me from it; and you know great Lady, if I ſhould depart and leave you to your ſelf through your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in believing old fabulous ſtories, it would fend to your utter ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Then ſaid the Empreſs, Moſt grave Lord and Councellour, paſs by your ſorrow and lamentation at this time, and I ſhall never fail you of your requeſt hereafter, but be adviſed by you: Then ſaid <hi>Radamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> pray God you may, elſe I fear it will happen to you as it did to the Lady and her Cat in the Kingdome of <hi>Utergo,</hi> who ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb facs="tcp:55822:32"/>her Cat as ſhe did her own life, till at laſt the Cat cut her Ladies throat. I pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaid the Empreſs, ſhew me that Example, that I ſhall gladly do, ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> for the furtherance of your knowledge, and it is this as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The third Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>IN the Kingdome of <hi>Utergo</hi> there lived a Lady who had but one onely Daughter, whom ſhe loved above her own eyes, and hearing there was a very learned woman, and one of great repute, lived not far from her own Court, to whom ſhe put her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be brought up, and inſtructed in all Arts and learning, and it proved that this learned woman was very skilful indèed, for ſhe was the greateſt Magician in all that Land, though unknown to the Lady, ſo that inſtead of teaching the childe natural Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, ſhe taught her all the whole art of Necromancy, and at the end of ſeven years ſhe learnt her how to transform her ſelf into the likeneſs of a Cat; and upon a time the Lady ſent for this learned woman to come to her, and bring her Daughter with her, for to ſee how ſhe had improved her ſelf in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:32"/>and being come, the Lady asked her Daughter, three queſtions: Firſt, what was moſt prone to nature when it was ſatiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? ſhe anſwered, eaſe, for when the belly is full, the bones deſtreth reſt. Secondly, how far it was to the bottom of the Sea: ſhe anſwered, a ſtones throw. Thirdly, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sked her how long the Sun and Moon were going round the world? ſhe anſwered, ſower and twenty hours: then ſaid the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, you have anſwered me well, doubtleſs thou wilt prove a cunning woman: then ſhe walked in her Parlour, and ſhewed the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs what a delicate and fine Cat ſhe had, and the Miſtriſs ſaid of a truth, it is a brave Cat; but after I return home I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with the fineſt Cat that ever was ſeen, for ſhe will wait at the Table, and can interpret Riddles, reſolving Anſwers and Queſtions, ſo that there is not the like of her in all the world, Then ſaid the Lady, pray ye let me have that Cat? that I ſhall not do, ſaid ſhe, except you ſuffer your Daughter to be with me one ſeven years more, then ſhall I preſent you with the Cat; the Lady very willingly gave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto, rendring great thanks: ſo the learned woman took leave, and away depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:55822:33"/>with her young Diſciple, and when ſhe came home, ſhe told her, that if ſhe would act her part, ſhe would teach her how ſhe might enjoy all the pleaſure the world did afford, and none was more ready to learn then ſhe was. Then ſaid the Magician, you muſt transform your ſelf to the likeneſs of a Cat, and I will preſent you to your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to which they both accorded: then the Magician took her, and haſted away to the Lady, and preſented her the Cat, being of four diſtinct colours, black, red, green, and yellow: Then ſaid the Lady, this is the fineſt Cat that ever I ſaw, and took it into her lap, feeding it with white bread and milk, and would never ſit down to meat but her Cat muſt be at her elbow; ſo the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician took her leave again, and the Lady gave her great thanks, ſo departed: ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the Cat began to play her pranks, for there was a maid living in the houſe, whoſe carriage was civil, and converſation honeſt, and a faithful ſervant all dayes of her life: this Cat had power to open any lock, and ſhut it again, ſo ſhe would open the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Cabinet, and take out money, and lay it in the way where the maid ſhould finde it, ſome time in the Garden, ſome time in the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:33"/>Stréet, and the Lady ſtill miſſing her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and having no ſuſpicion on the Maid in the leaſt, wondered what ſhould become of it; at laſt ſhe loſt her Bracelet out of her Cloſet, which the Cat had took and laid a mile from the houſe where the Maid ſhould come along; ſo the Maid when ſhe found it, little thought of her Ladies Bracelet, which oftentimes had béen inquired for, ſhe put it up in her Trunck; and after upon a time, as the Maid was taking out clothes, her Lady ſtood by her, and it chanced that the Bracelet fell beſide the Trunck, and the Cat ſnapt it up in her paws, and leapt upon the Ladies lap: when the Lady ſaw it ſhe cryed out, O thou graceleſs creature, I bleſs the Lord I have found thée out, have I kept thee for ſo many years, and intruſted thee with all I had in the world, and never had the leaſt ſuſpicion of thee; God knows what thou haſt robb'd me of in thy time. O thou wicked wretch! now thou ſhalt dye the ſhamefulleſt death as may be thought on. Then ſaid the Maid, what have I done, I never offended you in thought, word, nor deed, neither ever wronged you in all my life hitherto? O villain, ſaid the Lady, is not this my Bracelet, I have loſt for above
<pb facs="tcp:55822:34"/>this half year, and hore I have found it in thy Trunk! God knows what thou haſt rob'd me of beſides, for I have loſt a great deal of money; then ſhe call'd more company in and ſearched her Trunk fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and found many péeces of money, which ſhe knew by the marks; and when they ſaw that, they apprehended her, and ſent her to priſon for all dayes of her life; ſo the Lady continued her love towards the Cat, and would never eat of any dainties at her Table before ſhe had cut her Cat the firſt bit, at laſt it happened that ſhe ſate at Dinner and forgot to carve firſt to her Cat, wherefore ſhe leapt to the Ladies face and catcht her by the throat, that had it not béen for the help of ſome at the Table, the Cat had kill'd her: Then ſaid the Lady, Ile kéep this Cat no longer; then it is good ſaid her friends to deſtroy her: No, ſaid ſhe, for the ſake of the learned Miſtris which gave her me; then ſhe returned her back from whence ſhe came, and deſtred to have her Daughter home; when her Daughter came ſhe took her in her arms and kiſſed her, and cauſed her to lye in bed with her every night, and in token of a motherly love to a child, ſhe gave her a King of her finger out of
<pb facs="tcp:55822:34"/>love to wear, which King ſhe had kept for many years; and it happened after that this Daughter procéeded in her wicked art of witchcraft ſtill and could not break from it: So there was a Mill of the Ladies not far from the houſe, and every night this Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when her mother was aſléep, would go with others of her rabble, and at dead time of the night ſet the Mill a going, ripping the bags, and throwing all the Corn about the flour; at which the Miller wondered greatly, and complained on the morrow to the Lady and many others, ſaying, his Mill was haunted by evill ſpirits, doing great miſchief, that he was like to be undone; and they counſelled him to watch up one night with a good ſword and a light to ſée what it was; and about midnight there came in at the window a great Cat to his thinking, by and by another and another, till they were half a dozen, ſpitting and wawling like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and their eyes ſhining like coles of fire; then the Miller ſtruck at them, and they ſlew at his face, and in ſhort time deſtroy'd him: On the morrow the Lady ſent to the Mill to ſée how the Miller fared, and they found him dead, with his face and throat tore all to pieces, the next night another
<pb facs="tcp:55822:35"/>watcht, and on the morrow they went to ſée how he ſped, and they found him in the ſame condition; then they all marvelled greatly, ſo that none would live in that Mill. At laſt there came a ſtout fellow, and he would undertake to lye in the Mill all night if the Lady would give him the Mill, ſhe conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and away goes the fellow, with a great Sword and Candle, and entered the Mill; ſo about the old hour he heard the Mill at work to the purpoſe; ſo he took his Sword and Candle in his hand, and went damn out of his Chamber to ſée what gueſts he had got, and when he came into the Mill he ſaw nothing, but the Mill ſtood ſtill, and as ſoon as he had entered his Chamber, the Mill was at it again as hard as 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; then he ran back again with his ſword drawn, and there he beheld ſix great Cats and one little one, with ſuch ſparkling eyes glearing upon him, that he ne're ſaw the like before; whereupon he ſtruck at them, and they leapt at his face, and on every ſide of him, that he was fain to lay about him luſtily to defend himſelf; at laſt he worſted two, and they fled through the window, and the reſt fought ſo furiouſly, that they put him almoſt out of breath, but in the end
<pb facs="tcp:55822:35"/>they all fled through the window, and he following cloſe, ſmote the laſt and cut off her fore-foot; and ſo when day came, he went to look for the foot, and it proved to be a hand with a fair King upon the finger; when he ſaw that, then he knew they were Witches, ſo took on him little, and went home to the Lady, who asked him how it fared with him? He ſaid he was never ſo hard put to it in his life; how ſo ſaid the Lady? why ſaid he, there came ſeven Cats, and ſet the Mill to work as well as I could, and if I had not defended my ſelf ſtoutly, I had béen ſlain by them, but in the end I made them flye; and as the laſt went through the window, I cut off her fore-foot, look here it is: When the Lady ſaw that, ſhe knew the hand by the Ring, and ſhe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that night, when ſhe awak't ſhe felt her daughter come in the bed all in a ſweat, and very cold; with this thought ſhe was ſtrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with a fear, that the drops of ſweat trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down her face; ſo ſhe went to the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and asked her daughter how ſhe did? who ſaid, I am not well, pray let me alone; her mother ſaid, let me féel your hand, how your pulſes beat, and ſhe gave her the right hand, kéeping the other arm in the bed, and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:36"/>her mother ſaid, give me the other hand, and ſhe would not; then her mother went to ſée by force, and there was no hand; then her mother knew what Cat ſhe had kept before, and ſaid thou ſhalt dye by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before thou deeſt any more miſchief. O graceleſs Villain, what ſhame h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> brought upon me for having ſuch a wicked childe; ſo ſhe was ſentenced to be burnt at a ſtake, and as ſhe was led to execution, ſhe confeſt how ſhe had ſtole the money and bracelet, and laid it where the maid found it, ſo to be accus'd of theft and hang'd unjuſtly; but at laſt ſhe was burn'd to aſhes at a ſtake, and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent maid redéemed out of priſon.</p>
                  <p>Now ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> underſtand you what I have ſaids yes right well ſaid the Empreſs; then ſaid <hi>Radamentus</hi> I will ſhew you the declaration thereof.</p>
                  <div type="lesson">
                     <head>The Declaration of the Example.</head>
                     <p>THen <hi>Radamentus</hi> ſaid to the Empreſſe, Great Lady, I fear this will happen to you and your daughter as it did to this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who for the love of her onely daughter ſet her to School to be inſtructed in vertuous learning, and ſhe was tutored by a Witch in
<pb facs="tcp:55822:36"/>all the arts of Necromancy; in the firſt place ſhe rob'd her mother, and caus'd an innocent maid to father the theft; ſecondly, in her filthy transformation, had ſhe not béen prevented, ſhe had cut her mothers throat; thirdly, her horrid murther in the Mill; fourthly, the diſgrace and ſhame brought upon her mother and family; and fifthly, the utter ruins and deſtruction ſhe brought upon her own ſoul: and in the ſame manner do you labour to preſerve your daughter, and ſuffer her to reign, in all her filthy and deteſtable wayes till ſuch time the truth of all things breaks out, then be ſure you will receive utter ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, even to the ruine of your ſelf and the whole Empire; therefore I adviſe you to cut her off while ſhe is in the bud, leſt ſhe prove in the end to be a hard trée, and there is no cutting down of her. The Empreſs ſaid, you have ſhewed me a good Example, the Lady giving her Daughter too much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, afterwards would have cut her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers throat, and turned both witch, thief, and murther or; without doubt my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall not ſerve me ſo, and on the morrow ſhe commanded her officers to le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d her away to be burnt, who obey'd her command in all
<pb facs="tcp:55822:37"/>haſte: As ſhe was led through the ſtréets, attired in her winding-ſhéet, her Bible un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her arm, and the trumpets ſounding out her doleful knell, all the people cry'd out, alas, alas, the onely Daughter of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs is leading to execution: and as they lead her, the third Miſtris named <hi>Mardula</hi> came riding by; and as the Princeſs ſaw her, ſhe bowed her head to her, as much as to ſay, remember me; all the people cry'd ant, ſaying, O good Miſtris make haſte, and by your famous wiſdom ſave your Diſciple: ſo away ſhe poaſted and came before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, doing her reverence, and the Empreſs ſaid, O thou ungrateful Traytor, thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming availeth thée nothing, for thou ſhalt dye as bad a death as my wretched Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and I long till I be avenged on thée and all thy fellows. Then ſaid the Miſtris, I thought when I came to have béen better treated, and not to be upbraided in this kinds as I am: The Empreſs ſaid, do you not deſerve death, when as I delivered you my daughter wel, to be inſtructed in vertuous learning, and you have delivered her again unto me dumb and graceleſs, whoſe laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions ſounds all over the Empire: th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſaid the Miſtris, in that you ſay ſhe is
<pb facs="tcp:55822:37"/>dumb, I commit that to God, <hi>for he maketh the dumb to ſpeak, and the deaf to hear;</hi> and as you ſay ſhe is a laſcivious creature, I fain would know if the eye of man ever ſaw, or tongue can juſtifie any ſuch thing: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gracious Lady, if you put your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to death thus haſtily for the words of one man, it will happen to you as it did to a Knight and his God-ſon, which is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an Example. The Empreſs ſaid, pray ſhew me that Example, and the Miſtris ſaid, that I ſhall not do, but if you will cauſe your Daughter to be brought back again from death, then ſhall I gladly ſhew it you, which in time to come you will ſay 'tis a true one. Then the Empreſs commanded her daughter to be brought back and put in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and the Miſtris began as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the third Miſtris.</head>
                  <p>IT came to paſs upon a time, that as a Knight was travelling through a ſtrange Countrey, he chanced to loſe his way in a Wood, and could neither diſcover Churches nor Towns, the night being ſo dark, and he a ſtranger, knew not what to do, nor whither to go; and as he was complaining to himſelf, a
<pb facs="tcp:55822:38"/>Woodman iſſued through the thickets, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his complaint. and domanded the cauſe of it. O friend, ſaid the Knight, I am a ſtranger to the Countrey, and I have loſt my way, and know not whither to go for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations for me and my Horſe, which is almoſt loſt in the Brambles of this Wood. The man ſaid, Sir Knight, it is far to any Inne, and the wayes are bad; but if you pleaſe to go with me, I ſhall bring you to my Cottage, and give you the beſt accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation it doth yield. The Knight courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly returned him thanks, and went along with him, and when he came home, ſhewed the Knight a Chamber, and provided for his Horſe: but the Knight through diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Iourney did not go to bed but ſate up, and about midnight he heard a great cry in the houſe, he being in ſuch a lone houſe began to fear ſome danger might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and ſo knocked for to know what that cry did mean; and the Maid anſwered, that her Miſtriſſe was in Travail, and the Midwife was with her. This Knight being skill'd in Aſtrology, went down to ſée how the Planets did ſerve, it being a bright Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light night, and he ſaw a bad Planet going down, and a good one riſing; ſignifying, if
<pb facs="tcp:55822:38"/>
                     <figure/> the Childe was been under that, his fortune was to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nged; therefore he called the Maid and bid her tell the Midwife to held her hand one quarter of an hour, and the Childe would he born to good fortune: the Maid came out again, and told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> could not poſſibly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> again, and tell the Midwife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> half quarter of an hour, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be born to go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d fortune. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> again, and bren the him word that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> was delivered of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the bad Planet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſaid nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:39"/>the Childe: but on the morrow the Father of it came to him, ſaying, Sir, ſince you have vouchſafed to lodge in my houſe all night, be pleaſed to honour me ſo far as to name my Childe, who anſwered, that I ſhall gladly do. And when the day was come he named the Childe, and writ in a bit of Parchment his deſtiny, with a charge alſo, that he ſhould pray to God continually to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit him from that ſad fortune, ſo he ſealed it up in a piece of wax, &amp; tyed it about his neck with a Silk String, charging his Father and all his friends not to untye the ſtring to read what it was, till ſuch time the Childe was able to read it himſelf, deſtring them to kéep him at School very carefully, whereby he may attain to that knowledge as to read the writing perfectly himſelf; and thanking the Father for the favour done him, took his leave, and ſo departed. When the Childs was grown up and fit to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, he was put to School, and very carefully attended till he was ten years of age, at which time he was capable to read the writing that was about his neck: and upon a time as he was by himſelf, he took it off his neck, and opened it, and read it, wherein he found his deſtiny written in
<pb facs="tcp:55822:39"/>
                     <figure/> theſe words, My good Childe, ſerve God, and pray to him continually to paſs this fate over thée, elſe thy fortune is to be hanged. When the Childe had read this, he liſted up his eyes to heaven and begg'd a bleſſing from the Lord, and went home very ſad and melancholly, and deſtred of his Father to give him one new ſuit of clothes, and a little money in his pocket, and his bleſſing; his Father asked him the reaſon of his requeſt: then ſaid the Childe, pray give it me, for I will go ſeek my fortune; his Father did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Childe required, ſo he took
<pb facs="tcp:55822:40"/>
                     <figure/> leave of his friends, and parted from his Father. Well, go, ſaid he, and my bleſſing with thée; ſo the Boy travelled into a ſtrange Countrey, ſtill praying to God to acquit him of that unhappy fortune to which he was predicted to; and at laſt he came to a Knights houſe, and required a ſervice, the Knight asked him what he could do, he ſaid, ſwéep your Hall, draw Beer, and run upon your Arands, and what other ſervice I am able to do. The Knight ſaw him a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful boy, and very willingly entertained him, and he proved marvellous careful and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in whatſoever he took in hand, and at
<pb facs="tcp:55822:40"/>all ſpare times he would be upon his knées at prayers, deſiring God to paſs that unhappy fate over him. The Knight obſerving this, ſoon after plac'd him under Buttler, and there he continued in the ſame ruſe, praying to God continually, whereby the Knight had a great diſcerning eye on him. In this place he had not been many years, but the head Buttler dyed, and he Knight put him in his place, and being there he was obedient to his Maſter, courteous to his fellow ſervants, &amp; pleaſing to all, but the baker and the brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er murmured greatly, ſaying, how may this be, yonder fellow was taken up as a poor beggar boy at the door but the other day, and firſt he was under Buttler, now he is head Buttler, what will he come to: but this paſt on, he grew in favour ſtill, and being a Schollar, his Maſter made him under Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which place he diſcharged with great truſt and faithfulneſs; then his two adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries murmured ten times more, yet he grew in favour more ſtill with the Knight, till at laſt the head Steward dyed; then he was prefer'd in that place, and from that time forwards his adverſaries ſought his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: yet when he was in this place, he never waxed proud nor ambitious, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:55822:41"/>truſty, humble, meek, and lowly, and when he had ſerved in the place of head Stewardſhip the ſpace of five years, he had a minde to go ſée his own Countrey, and therefore delivered up all his accounts juſt and ſquare, he asked leave of the Knight, who granted his requeſt very willingly, and lent him a Horſe, and gave him great ſtore of money to go with, ſaying, Thou haſt béen a juſt and faithful ſervant to me, go, and my beſt word with thée; and when his horſe was tyed at the door, and he ready to depart, there came to him the Baker and the Brewer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully to take their leaves of him, ſaying they muſt drink with him before parting, and as he was drinking with one in the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the other opened his Portmantle, and put therein a great Gilt Bowl, and ſo ſhut it again: then he went and drank with him, and ſo departed; but he had not béen gone above a mile, but theſe two fellows made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition for the Bowl, and the Knight ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who ſhould have it, who ſhould, ſaid they, but your truſty friend and ſervant, that is newly gone, who hath béen as very a thief as ever breathed ſince he came to you, and has robb'd you daily, though you would not believe it; therefore you will not believe
<pb facs="tcp:55822:41"/>this except you ſaw it, therefore pray ride along with us, and we'l bring him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and that you ſhall ſée he has the Bowl: ſo the Knight rid after him, and overtook him, and praid him to come back, for he had a little buſineſs with him; ſo when he came, they ſearched his Portmantle, and found the Bowl: when the Knight ſaw that, he admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, and ſaid, O thou wicked wretch, I have béen told how thou haſt rob'd me daily, and impoveriſhed my Eſtate, but I would never believe it, now I ſée it plainly with my eyes, for which fact thou ſhalt be hanged at the Gallows.</p>
                  <p>The young man ſtood up, and ſaid, of this fact I am innocent, and thou eternal God, who holdeth the ſecrets of all men hearts in thy hands, knows that I am guiltleſs, ſend me juſtice now, O great Lord of heaven and earth, that thy everlaſting truth may take place, and this hidden treachery be brought to light. And as they were leading him away to priſon, he ſaid, Well, now I perceive that Fortune is a Fortune, let the world go how it will; and his Maſter hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, ſaid, what mean you by that? and he ſaid, when my Mother was in Travail of me, there was a ſtrange Knight lodged in
<pb facs="tcp:55822:42"/>tha houſe, and did foreſée my deſtiny by his art in the Planets, and at the requeſt of my Father he was my God-father, and then writ in a little piece of Parchment my ſad fate in theſe words following, My good childe, ſerve God, and pray continually that the ſad fate may paſs over thee, for thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is to hanged: and he ſealed it up in war, and tyed it with a ſilk String, and put it about my neck, charging my Father, that no one ſhould read it till I was capable to read it my ſelf; wherefore I came to travel, and alſo obeying the words, and praying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to God to eſcape it, I ſée it doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me undeſerved, as you now ſee. The Knight hearing this, demanded to ſée the piece of writing, which ſpecified his deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and he took the ſtring from obout his neck: and gave it the Knight, who as ſoon as he ſaw it, he ſaid, O the merry of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal God of Heaven, whoſe love to his ſervants is incompréhenſible, this is my own hand-writing; I writ thy deſtiny, and I am thy God-farther, O bring him back again, let us examine the cauſe better; then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e called the two falſe accuſers before him, and ſtrictly examined each of them, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſad puniſhment if they would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:42"/>and at laſt they confeſt it were they ſtole the Cup, and put it in his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtmantle; for which they were both hanged, and the young man ſaved: And then ſaid the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, underſtand you what I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve ſaid? yes, right well, ſaid the Empreſs, Now I do perceive that very often the wicked commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the fact, and the innocent are Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. You have ſhamed me a good example, therefore my Daughter ſhall not dye. Great Lady, ſaid the Miſtris, if you do ſo, you will do well, and I thank yo for ſparing your Daughter this day for my ſake, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to God I commend you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fourth Complaint of Radamentus</head>
                  <p>WHen <hi>Radamentus</hi> heard the young Princeſs was not dead, but rather pardoned, he waiked up and down the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den like a man bereaved of his wits, and made great lamentation; the noiſe thereof came to the Empreſs our, and ſhe went in all haſte to him, and comforted him, ſaying, My gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, Lord and Counſellour, why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it's you this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an? if behoveth our a man, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as you are, ſo rarely well dig, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in wiſdom and diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etion, to gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:43"/>out ſuch ſad complaints? O Madam, ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> why ſhould you tell me ſo, will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t make a ſtone move, or a wall of braſs ſpeak, to ſee that your judgement is ſo much ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>upified, as not to be adviſed by my grave Counſel, knowing no man ought to tell you more then my ſelf, that you ſuffer ſuch peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs to remain not qualified nor oppreſſed: O that I had dyed before I had been elected to come into theſe parts, for what honour or reputation I ever gained formerly, I ſhall now receive ten times as much ſhame and diſhonour; but I fear it will happen to you as it did unto a Lady in <hi>Theſaly</hi> with her Déer, which is mentioned in the Example. Then ſaid the Empreſs, I pray ſhew me that example for my learning, I may be the better inſtructed. If I ſhould, ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> it would avail nothing, for I ſhewed you one yeſterday laſt, and it came to no effect; nevertheleſs I ſhall ſhew you this, which is as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The fourth Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>SOmetime in <hi>Rome</hi> there lived a great Lady which had a famous Park of Déer, that a worthier was not in all the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:43"/>land; ſhe had alſo a very gallant Hound, which was preſented to her by the beſt Huntſman in the world: and this Lady de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting much in hunting, appointed a day for the tryal of this brave Dog; and when the day was come they rouzed a Buck, and followed the Chace, up the Hills, down the Dales, through the Thickets, Bracks, and Boggs, the like hunting ne'r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was known in that part of the world, for the Dog hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon hot ſent ſeven dayes together, till all the followers were tyred both foot and horſe, and left the whole Game to the Dog; yet ſtill the Buck maintained his ground, and the Dog his Chace, throughout the Kingdom of <hi>Theſaly</hi> three hundred mils an end; the Lady and her Noble Barons gave off all for loſt, ſome of them cryed, we ſhall never ſee the Buck again; ſaid the Lady, I ſhall never have my Dog again: and when they had yielded all as loſt, there came a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he knowing her ſo delightful in Hunting, and the tenure of it was, that there came a Buck chaſed by a Dog, through ſome part of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that they were come into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Theſaly:</hi> The Lady hearing this, ſaid, Doubtleſs, this Dog and this Buck by
<pb facs="tcp:55822:44"/>
                     <hi>all</hi> deſcription ſhould be mine, and as ſhe was thus muſing, the Keeper brought in word that the Buck and Dog was come; then the Lady rejoyced and ran into the Park to ſee the Buck and Dog, and there they found the Buck leapt juſt ever the wall, and fell down, and the dog ran to the wall, and he fell down, onely wearied, but not to death: then ſaid the Keeper, this Buck is the beſt runner in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>Theſaly;</hi> and the Lady ſaid, this Dog is the beſt in all the world, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Nobles and Barons that ever came there a hunting praiſed that Dog and loved him wonderfully. Now there was an obſervation on this Dog, for he loved the Park ever after, and the ſame buck he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore chaſed above all others; ſo that he was obſerv'd to go every night about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, to defend the Déer from any ravenous beaſt which ſhould chance to come, as Wolves or ſuch like Creatures, and this did he conſtantly upon his own accord, ſo that ſuch a Dog was never heard of before. And it chanced after, that the ſame Huntſman which gave the Lady this brave Dog, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented her with another wolf-dog, young and tender, and of a moſt curious ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe and form, which alſo won the affections of the Lady marvellouſly, ſo that ſhe loved him as
<pb facs="tcp:55822:44"/>ſhe lov'd her life; and whoſoever ſhould tell her that this wolf-dog would prove the better Courſer, ſhe would rejoyce, and give them great rewards; ſo that her love to the Hound began to decline, for he was wont to quarrel with her young dog, being of two contrary natures, for which ſhe would kick him and much reject him; but the young dog grew apace well formed, fair and comely: Not far from her Court lived ſeven wiſe Miſtriſſes, whom ſhe ſent for to paſs their judgements upon this young Dog, what
<figure/> they thought of him? And the firſt ſaid, it was the faireſt dog that ever ſhe ſaw, and it would make a good Courſer; then the ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:55822:45"/>ſaid, it was the comelieſt Dog that ever ſhe ſaw, and he would make a ſtately kéeper; the third ſaid, it was the talleſt Dog that ever ſhe ſaw, and would be fit for a Princely Game; the fourth ſaid, it was the ſtrongeſt Dog that ever ſhe ſaw, and would be a brave companion in a forreſt; the fifth ſaid, it was the furicuſeſt Dog that ever ſhe ſaw, and was fit to kéep a treaſury; the firth ſaid, it was a dog in her judgement excéeded all others; and the ſeventh ſaid, it was a Dog, if well taught and preſerved, would paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel the whole world for his equal. Then ſaid the Lady, I thank you all for your great accommodations you give of my dog; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall prize him as I do the greateſt Iewel I have, but I have an excellent Hound beſides, which on his own accord doth watch my Déer every night, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from the Wolves, and the like ſavage beaſts, and they two can never agrée. Then ſaid the firſt Miſtris, the Hound is ſomething ancient, and probable might not live long; the wolf-dog is young and iuſty, and the beſt of his dayes are to come; and ſince they cannot live both together quietly, it is expedient one ſhould dye, therefore let the Hound be deſtroy'd: Then the Lady
<pb facs="tcp:55822:45"/>gave command that the Hound ſhould be hang'd immediately; and ſoon after the Hound was dead, many Déer were loſt out of the Park, therefore they put the Wolf-dog to watch, yet for all that a Déer in two or thrée nights was conſtantly loſt, and ſtill the Lady wondered how this might be, and the Wolf-dog watching too; ſo ſhe put a man to watch all night in a trée, to eſpy out what beaſt came to veſtry her Déer, and by the light of the Moon he diſcovered the Wolf-dog upon a luſty Buck, having tore his throat; when the morning came, the Lady ſent for him to know what he had ſeen; and be ſaid, I have ſéen what it is that kills the Déer now: declare ſaid the Lady what it is, and he ſaid, it is even your own Wolf-dog, whom you put to watch them; then the Lady looked ſad in the face, and began to complain greatly, ſaying, Alas, have I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd the Shepheard, and put a Wolf in his ſtead; have I then through the wicked advice of yonder fooliſh women hang'd my good and truſty Hound, which looked to my Herd, and preſerv'd them from the ravenous wolves; the braveſt Courſer and flower of all Dogs in <hi>Theſaly,</hi> and have here put a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous murtherer of my Deer to keep the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:46"/>Park: and with theſe words ſhe ſtruck the Dog three or four blows with her Cane, and the maſterleſs Cur grumbled as if it had béen a Lyon; and then ſaid the Lady, how now Déer-killer, and ſmote him again, but before ſhe ſtruck the fifth blow, he rear'd upon her breaſt, and ſlew her before the eyes of her ſervants: Then all people curſed the Counſellours which adviſed the Lady to kéep that evil Dog, and to kill the good Hound. Then ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> underſtand you what I have ſaid? yes right well, ſaid the Empreſs, then ſaid he, I will ſhew you the Declaration thereof.</p>
                  <div type="lesson">
                     <head>The Declaration of the Example.</head>
                     <p>THe Lady delightful in hunting, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your ſelf in all vertuous recreation, ſo that all Kings of the Earth do hear of your ſame, as the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> did of her Game; the large and ſpacious Park is your Empire, and the Déer therein are your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; the good Hound watching them, is your wiſe and good diſcretion, defending them from ravenous wolves, in kéeping us in peace and ſafety from the bloody hands of cruel Tyrants; the fair and maſterleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:55822:46"/>Wolf-dog is your ſtubborn and graceleſſe Daughter, who by her ill examples and bad precedents will delude your good Subjects, and in the end deſtroy them as the Dog did the Deer; the fooliſh women that counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lady to kill the good Hound, and let the Wolf-dog live, is your ſeven wiſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſes, which daily labour to adviſe you to ſuppreſs your vigilancy and wiſe care of your Subjects, and let your filthy laſcivious Daughter live, whereby ſhe may reign in bloody tyranny, and glut her ſelf with the fleſh of your people: the man in the Tree that diſcovered the Dog in killing the Déer, was my ſelf in my Chamber window, eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Daughter that ſhameleſs wretch in the Garden under a trée ſomething ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, with a man committing the foul ſin of fornication, and all other beaſtly behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; for which deteſtable and abominable act ſhe ought to dye according to the Law; for if ſhe live, ſhe will by her ill wayes give baſe examples, and deſtroy many others: if then you correct her for it, ſhe will like unto the Wolf-dog leap upon your breaſt, and cut your throat. Then ſaid the Empreſs, that Dog the Lady loved ſo dearly cut her throat at laſt, but my Daughter ſhall not do ſo:
<pb facs="tcp:55822:47"/>Then ſhe commanded her Officers to lead her away to the ſtake; and as ſhe was led through the ſtreets with trumpets ſounding her doleful funeral, all the people ran out making a ſad noiſe, crying, alas, alas, the Empreſs onely Daughter is led again to the Stake. Then the fourth Miſtris leapt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her horſe, and haſted away to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and did obeyſance to the Empreſs, who ſaid, O thou curſed old wretch, little thanks ſhalt thou have for thy ill inſtructing my Daughter, and bringing her to what ſhe is now gone to; I delivered her to you finely taught, modeſt and well mannered, and you delivered her again to me ill taught, full of vice and dumb, and a ſhameleſs whore, for which this day ſhe is to dye, to the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Empire, and diſgrace of all her lineage; I would the day of her birth had been the day of her burial. O gracious Lady then ſaid the Miſtris, I little thought of this entertainment, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I have not deſerved the leaſt of this your diſpleaſure; and for why your Daughter ſpeaketh not, I commit the cauſe to God, and in ſhort time you ſhall know the reaſon, but the time is not come yet: ſhe is accus'd ſhe hath committed the ſoul ſin of fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:47"/>that is falſe, and is not to be proved; therefore you ought not to put your onely Daughter to death for the words of one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon, though it were Iuſtice; and if you pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> her to death for one mans ſaying, it ſhall be worſe to you then to the Queen, who for putting too much confidence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours had her onely Daughter cut in pieces before the Altar, and her ſelf after ſtoned to death. Then ſaid the Empreſs, declare that Example for my learning, that I ſhall not do, ſaid the Miſtris, unleſs you ſend for your Daughter back again, otherwiſe ſhe may be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d before I make an end, then ſhould I talk to you in vain. Then the Empreſs commanded her Daughter to be brought back again and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in priſon, while the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris ſpake as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the fourth Miſtris.</head>
                  <p>SOme time there lived in the Kingdom of <hi>Thracia</hi> a famous Queen named <hi>Hicuba,</hi> who built a ſtrong City of defence, double wall'd, and moated round; ſhe was a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Queen, and at variance with none, ſave onely the King of <hi>Lycia,</hi> being a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome Prince; and be came againſt her
<pb facs="tcp:55822:48"/>with an invincible Army, and beſſeged her round; wherefore ſhe call'd before her in Councel her two Counſellors named <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinor</hi> and <hi>Eneus;</hi> and they aſſembled all the noble Citizens to adviſe how to preſerve their City, and give their enemies battel; and when they had fortified their walls, and planted their Guards, <hi>Anthinor</hi> iſſued out with ten thouſand men, and made a great ſlaughter among his enemies, and ſo return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back into the City; then their enemies recruited again, and fell on to ſcale the walls, but were driven back by the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: then <hi>Eneus</hi> went out and ſought with great valour, but loſt many men, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd into the Town. At laſt <hi>Anthinor</hi> addreſſed himſelf to the Queen, and told her it were good to conclude peace with the enemies, for they had loſt many noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of honour, among whom were the Queens two Sons, for which they made great moan; and therefore he adviſed the Queen to conclude a peace, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may depart without deſtroying the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for they could not maintain it againſt ſuch an invincible power, though the City was well fortified, and ſtrength enough to have beaten twice as many; yet the Queen
<pb facs="tcp:55822:48"/>believed theſe two evil Counſellors, which proved arrand Traytors; than the harmleſs Queen asked them who they ſhould have to go treat for them? Then <hi>Eneus</hi> ſtood up and ſaid, if it ſeemeth good to the Queen and to all you Citizens, for the honour of the Queen, the ſafeguard of our City, and the preſervation of our lives, <hi>Anthinor</hi> and I being expert in all Laws and Cuſtoms upon ſo weighty a matter as this, will go forth. The Queen liked well of what he ſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing more confidence in them then any
<figure/> other, and all the Citizens accorded to it: and <hi>Anthinor</hi> and <hi>Eneus</hi> went forth and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:49"/>ſounded a parley, and the Enemies Heralds came and fetcht them in; and <hi>Anthinor</hi> ſaid, we have wrought ſo about with our Queen, that we have obtained Irave to come and couclude a league or truce with you; but if you will grant us two our demands, as we ſhall ask of you, we will betray the City in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hands, to do with it as it ſeemeth good to you; then they all promiſed to grant their demands. Then ſaid <hi>Anthinor,</hi> you ſhall give us a thouſand marks in Gold, and withall our Rights and Priviledges, and ſave all the lives of our Friends and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, with the preſervation of all our Houſes, Lands, and Poſſeſſions; then ſaid their Enemies, all theſe things are granted, and we are ready to ſwear the confirmation of it, which they immediately did: Then ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinor,</hi> we muſt be very private in this thing, for we muſt make a counterfeit truce with ye, and you muſt ſend this word in anſwer to our meſſage, thus:</p>
                  <p>That you require a hundred thouſand marks of gold to pay your Army, and ten thouſand meaſures of wheat to make them bread, and to ſet up a brazen horſe within the City in the Temple of <hi>Interva;</hi> and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe ſaid <hi>Anthinor</hi> muſt be caſt hollow,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:49"/>wherein a thouſand men may ſtand all arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and when it is in the Temple, and you have receiv'd your gold and wheat which I will order; then you muſt draw your Army off the Town, as they may ſuppoſe you are going away: then when the Citizens think all is ſecure, and are in bed aſleep, then ſhall the armed men in the brazen Horſe come forth, and <hi>Eneus</hi> and I will give you the ſign by a light off the wall; and when you ſee that, advance with all your Army on the back ſide of the Town, and we will open the Gates again you come; then do with the City as you ſee good, onely remember <hi>Eneus</hi> and I of our contract: and ſaid <hi>Anthinor,</hi> with thoſe words, we will depart, &amp; acquaint the Queen of it, and we ſhall come forth to morrow again to acquaint you of her anſwer; ſo took leaps of them, and departed ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> into the City, and fold the Queen what the Enemies requeſted, which was one hundred thouſand marks of Gold, and ten thouſand meaſures of Wheat, and they would depart home into their own Countrey, onely they would leave behinde them a brazen Horſe, which they had pruvided as a memorandum or mark of Conqueſt. Then the Queen ſighed deeply, and ſaid, What, have I loſt ſo
<pb facs="tcp:55822:50"/>many of my deareſt friends, and ſo much of the ſtately walls of my City domolliſhed, and now muſt I be conſtrain'd to pay ſo much Gold and Wheat unto my very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and hire them to go home into their Country<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> O was is me that ever I was born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but ſince it muſt be ſo, go tell them <hi>Anthinor,</hi> I do grant their demands; then <hi>Anthinor</hi> and <hi>Eneus</hi> went forth again, and ſaid to the Enemies, your requeſt is granted all what we have contrived, and you are to appoint the day to receive it, that we may make it ready; and after you have that, then we'l be for the City: ſo the day was appointed, and all was got ready, they receiving it all, then they draw the brazen Horſe into the City, and plat't it in the Temple, though little thought the harmleſs Quéen what holliſh plot lay in the belly of the Horſe. On the morrow all the Enemies drew off from the City towards night, and the poor Citizens ſuppoſing they were all departed towards their own Countrey, rejoyced all, and through watchfulneſs being up very many nights before, went to bed, and at midnight in the dead time of ſléep, <hi>Anthinor</hi> went to the brazen Horſe, and call'd forth that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand armed men, and <hi>Eneus</hi> went upon the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:50"/>back tower, and held up in his hand a bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing torch, which gave intelligences to the bloody Enemy; ſo they came and entred the Town, that all the ſtréets were full, and then <hi>Anthinor</hi> and <hi>Eneus</hi> the bloody Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſhewed them their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſes and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but for the harmleſs Quéen in her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace was no reſpect at all; and this Quéen had a fair and beautiful Daughter named <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> the like was not in all the world; ſhe wicked <hi>Anthinor</hi> would have radiſht ſome time before the ſiege, and ſhe refuſing, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to work this their utter deſtruction; and as the Quéen and her Daughter were at prayers, they heard a woful cry in the City, then they were ſtruck with jealouſie of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Anthinors</hi> treachery; ſo the Quéen ran into the Temple, and <hi>Paleſtina</hi> the young Lady poor ſoul ran and hid her ſelf in an old Tower, by which time the Enemy had not left alive neither man, woman, nor childs throughout the whole City. Then <hi>Anthinor</hi> the Traytor came to the Temple, and ſeeing the Quéen there, asked where her Daughter was? who replied, O un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Traytor, is not thy wicked bowels glutted yet with tyranny? Then he went to the old Tower, and there found her and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:51"/>drag'd her out, and gave her to the Enemy, who led her to the Altar, and before her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers own eyes they cut her in four quarters, and threw them about the Temple: the Quéen at the horrid ſight fell down in a ſwound, and when ſhe recovered life again, ſaid, Now Villains glu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your ſelves with tyranny, ſo fore the hair off her dead, and the clothes of her bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and went ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ark mad out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; wherefore the wicked Tyrants carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her into a ſtrange Iſland, and there miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her to death, and after burnt her City to the ground, and retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n'd home into their own Countrey. And then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris ſaid to the Empreſs, underſtand you what I have ſaid? how a Queen by putting too much confidence, and took too much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of two evil Counſellors, came at laſt to have her Daugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er cut in pieces before her own eyes, herſelf ſtoned to death, her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects maſſacred, and her whole City deſtroy'd; thererefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e advis'd, and put not your own D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter thus to death for the words of one Counſellor, leſt it happen to you as it did to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> harmleſe Queen. The Empreſs ſaid, you have ſhown me a good Example, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eves my heart to think of it, for they were the wickedeſt Counſellors that
<pb facs="tcp:55822:51"/>ever were, ſurely I will take no ſuch advice; for my Daughter ſhall not dye. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris ſaid, if you perform that you will do wiſely, and I thank you for ſparing your Daughter this day for my ſake, and ſo I commit you to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fifth Complaint of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RAdamentus</hi> hearing the young Princeſs was not dead, forthwith retired into his Chamber, ſighing and ſobbing moſt bitterly, and cauſed all his apparel and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries to be made ready, and his Wagons and Horſes brought up, as though he was juſt going into his own Countrey: The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants perceiving their Lord was departing from the Court, acquainted the Empreſs that <hi>Radamentus</hi> their Lord was preparing for his own Countrey; when the Empreſs perceived that, ſhe baſted to his Chamber, and ſaid to him, O my grave Lord, I thought you had been more tender of my ſafety, and the Government of the Empire, then to go and leave me thus; to which he anſwered, 'Tis true, I tender your welfare as much as I do my life, and you know I have had a care of your reputation, and the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:52"/>ſafety of the Empire, but now I ſée you are going in the high way to ſhame me, and diſhonour your ſelf, and ruin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the whole Realm; the world knowing I am your aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and do think 'tis all my advice in what you do, ſupporting Bawdry, and other vices, and in the very Court it ſelf; had it béen Vertus, the world had ne're taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice on't: but being Vice, the tongue of every inferiour fellow do noiſe it abroad like the breath of a Trumpet, or a Herald at arms, through all the parts of the world: therefore I go from you, for I had rather hear of your ruine then ſée it; you will be ruled by the words of the fooliſh Miſtriſſes, till at laſt it will happen to you as it did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Roman Lady and her Daughter, which Example is mentioned: and the Empreſs ſaid, pray ſhew me that Example for my bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding: And he ſaid, though I ſhall ſhew you all the Examples in the world, and give you all the advice I may imagine, you though it tend to the preſervation of both Life and Kingdom, as indéed it doth; yet you would not be ruled by me, nor follow my counſel: nevertheleſs I will ſhew you this Example, provided henceforth, you do not delight nor hear the Miſtriſſes, whoſe id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:52"/>Fables doth ſubvert your wiſe judgement: the Example is as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The fifth Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>SOmetimes in <hi>Rome</hi> there lived a famous Lady, whoſe worth and renown was ſpread far and near, being beloved of all people, for ſhe was vertuous in converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, modeſt in behaviour, gracious to her people, and amiable to all; and in reference to the poor, ſhe was adorned with a frée and bountiful liberality, ſo that ſhe had the prayers of all: This Lady had two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both of them very beautiful and comely; the eldeſt ſhe kept at home with her, and the youngeſt ſhe put abroad to be taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, having a motherly car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, this Lady ſent for her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter home, expecting ſhe had learnt much for her edification; but when ſhe came home, alas, ſhe was ne'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the better, ſo ſhe grieved very much for her Daughter, in regard of the tender love ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are her; and therefore ſhe would kéep her at home, being the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and ſet the other abroad: which being done, this young Girle began to do nothing but play, having what liberty ſhe pleaſed;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:53"/>at laſt ſhe grew to maturity, and then ſhe would not go abroad without money; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Mother gave her money from time to time: at laſt ſhe had wayes to ſpend more then her Mother allowed her if it had béen twice as much, for ſhe kept a private lover in the City which her mother knew not of, and many nights when her Mother was aſleep, ſhe would riſe and take the Keyes from under the Ladies head, and go out to her love, and towards break of day come in again, her mother never perceiving it, but towards morning ſhe wondered how her Daughter came ſo cold, and asked her what was the reaſon ſhe was ſo cold; ſhe ſaid, the Cramp had taken her in her leg, and being loath to wake her, ſhe roſe and walked about the Chamber to drive it away, ſo that excuſe paſt for currant. The next night ſhe awak't, and miſt her out of the houſe, and wondering how ſhe got out, put up her hand to feel for her Keyes, they were gone; ſo when her Daughter came in about break of day again, ſhe asked her, O Lord Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where have you been now? Truly ſaid ſhe, I had a tooth did ake ſo grievouſly, that my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw I thought would have broke, and you bring ſo ſound a ſleep, I was loath to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb
<pb facs="tcp:55822:53"/>ye; therefore I took the Keyes and went forth to the Chyrurgion to draw it, but I could not make him hear me: ſo this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond excuſe paſt as currant as the former, and her Mother ſaid no more of it. Vpon another time ſhe eſpied her Mothers Key of her Cabinet, and ſhe took it and preſt it in Clay that it made an impreſſion; and from this impreſſion ſhe got another Key made whereby ſhe could go to the Cabinet of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney when ſhe pleaſed; and her Mother miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing money ſo off, little thought of her own Daughter, but ſometime fathered the crime upon the Maid, ſometime upon the Man, that the Family was never but in ſtrife and variance: and upon a time ſhe went to her Mothers Cabinet for more money, and went away and left her Key behinde her in the Cabinet; her-Mother ſéeing a key in her Cabinet, and knew ſhe had her own in her Pocket, let it alone, and watcht behinds the Curtain to ſée who would fetch it out; by and by, in comes her Daughter, and ſnatcht the Key out, but her Mother catcht hold of her, and ſaid, O thou graceleſs wrecth, is it thée that haſt robb'd me theſe two years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, now I have found thee out, O wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked imp; I have béen often cold of thee, but
<pb facs="tcp:55822:54"/>I would never believe it till now I do ſée it, for which thou ſhalt dye a ſhameful death: but there was living not far off, an old woman, whom this young imp was wont to take advice of in all her wicked pranks; therefore in this time of neceſſity ſhe did ſend for her to come, and by her craft and cunning to ſave her life. When ſhe came ſhe ſaid, O vertuous Lady, let not your wrath be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uriouſly bent againſt her, ſhe is your Daughter whom you have bore of your body, and gave her ſuck nine moneths from your breaſt, for we were all guilty of faults in our infancy; therefore let her not come to ſhame for the firſt time, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Law will give reprieve to the verieſt Felon for the firſt fault, much more a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Mother ought to do for a Childe; and if ſhe ſhould thus dye, it will acrew great ſhame to her Family, and you will be brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with rebuke for tyranny: Vpon theſe words the good Mother was pacified, and pardoned her. It happened afterwards as the Lady was walking in the evening in her Garden, ſhe eſpied her Daughter l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng with a ſtrange man under a Buſh, then ſaid ſhe, and cryed out with a loud voice, O thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſcivious creature, worſe then any beaſt, I
<pb facs="tcp:55822:54"/>have pardoned thée for Theft already, and now thou art fallen into Whoredom, if I ſuffer this, all people will curſe me, and the Paps that gave thee ſuck; therefore thou ſhalt dye, for I had rather ſee thée hanged then I ſhould be ſound guilty of thy crimes. Then the old woman came again, and ſaid, O good Lady, ſave her life, conſider ſhe is young, and what ſhe hath done, is through ignorance and fooliſhneſs; but remember the old Proverb, <hi>A naughty boy may make a good man,</hi> likewiſe ſhe may amend and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good woman; and remember what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He that is without fault, let him throw the firſt ſtone;</hi> therefore let her ſhame be hidden this time, and if ever ſhe commit the like again do your pleaſure upon her: ſo through theſe ſtrong deluſions and fooliſh perſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions, the good Lady was again perſwaded, and pardoned her, but ſaid to the old woman, it is very ſeldom that any who are addicted to Theft and Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but commonly are guilty of Murder alſo, God grant that I never hear of no ſuch thing by her, though I fear it greatly: to prevent which, the godly Mother kept her within doors ſo ſtrict, that ſhe could not go abroad to her lover to féed him with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb facs="tcp:55822:55"/>as ſhe was wont to do; therefore he would come ſo her and ſpeak to her through the window, where ſhe threw him many of her Mothers pieces of Plats and other things; then the Lady marvelled greatly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow her things ſhould be loſt, and her Daughter never go out of doors, no farther then to the great window, where ſhe did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, ſhe ſtood every night: and it came to paſs that one night the Lady her ſelf was ſtanding under that window late, bearing the pretty Nightingale c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rping her ſeveral notes; and the Daughter ſuppoſing ſhe had béen her lover, threw out the great ſtiver Goblet; the Lady perceiving out of what window it came, took it up and came in with it, and askt for her Daughter, and the maid ſaid ſhe was in the middle window; call her to me, ſaid the Lady, when ſhe came, ſhe bid her go fetch her ſome wine in the Gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and ſhe ſaid, ſhe had béen looking for that and it could not be found: then the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Goblet and ſhewed her, ſaying, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t thou never lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thy tricks, thou graceleſs villain, now ſhalt thou dye ſurely a ſhameful death, the juſt reward of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Then news came again to the old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that the Ladies Daughter was to dye,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:55"/>and ſhe came in all haſte, crying to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſave her li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> but once more, and ſhe would undertake to adviſe her, and bring her to goodneſs her ſelf: Vpon this the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy pardoned her once more. Now this Daughter loved a man which was poor, and both a Thief and Murderer, whom her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not ſuffer her to marry with him without her conſent; ſhe had nothing to maintain him with, neither had he of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; therefore ſhe took counſel of the old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man what to do, who adviſed her to take a little of her poiſoned ball, and when her Mother called for Béer, to put in two drams, ſaying, that will diſpatch your Mother, then you may have all, and take your lover. The wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp was glad of this advice, and did execute it; her mother having took it, called for ſome more drink, the poiſon wrought ſo hot in her guts: when ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lled the cup again, ſhe put in more, and the harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Lady took it out of the hand of the bloody villain, as from a friend, ſo drank it up, and gave up the ghoſt, being aged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>eſcors and ten: for which horrid fact the wicked wretch was hurned at a ſtake. Thus was a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Lady firſt robb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d of her goods, and after murdered by a wicked Daughter ſhe beſt
<pb facs="tcp:55822:56"/>loved. Then ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> underſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e what I have ſaid, yes right well, ſaid the Empreſs, that was the wickedſt Daughter that ever I heard of; to prevent ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, my Daughter ſhall not live a day langer: therefore ſhe commanded her Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to lead her away to be burnt, and as ſhe was leading through the ſtréets, the people ran out, and cryed, alas, alas, the Empreſs Daughter is leading again to be burnt; and as ſhe paſt by, the fifth Miſtris met her, and haſted away to the Empreſs, doing reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as the others were went: then ſaid the Empreſs, you are come, but it ſhall be the price of your life: the Miſtris ſaid, O Lady, I have not deſerved to dys, for your Daughter hath not committed thoſe crimes which ye ſay ſhe hath done, as hereafter you ſhall finde; and that ſhe ſpeaketh not is of her wiſdom, and know ye ſhe will ſpeak when her time cometh: and as for the ſin of Fornication, believe it not, for a wiſe Virgin as ſhe is, would never attempt ſo ſhameful a deed, and if ye put her to death for the words of one man, it ſhall happen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> worſe then it did the Quéen of <hi>China.</hi> Then ſaid the Empreſs, pray ſhew me that Example; that I ſhall not do, ſaid wiſe <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bora,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:56"/>unleſs you call your Daughter back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain alſe before I make an end your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may be dead: then the Empreſſ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her Daughter to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> brought b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck and put in priſon; thea <hi>Debora</hi> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the fifth Miſtris.</head>
                  <p>SOmetime in <hi>China</hi> lived a vertuous Quéen, reuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ned far and near; for whoſe wiſdom and good diſcretion ſhe was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to a great Eaſtern King, who b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d a grave Counſellour, without whom be would do nothing: this vertuous Quéen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing married to this great King, ſoon after there aroſe a great Rebellion in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from whence he came, whereby he was conſtrained to go to ſuppreſs the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which ſoon he did, and to ſettle the uniformity, ſtaid there for the ſpace of half a year, by which time his Queen was grown big with childe: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is old Counſellour whom the King left at home as Guarding of her, wrote Letters to the King, that ſhe was very familiar with a Nobleman in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, whoſe name wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Palemed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thought what ſhe wont withall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:57"/>Thus did he through wicked trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, thinking to himſelf, the King was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and would be the more filled with jealouſie, and if he could deſtroy the Quéen and that ſhe went withal, ſoon after the King would dye, then ſaid he. I ſhall rule the Land; and from that time forth he ſought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir deſtruction. Now when the King had received his Letter he haſted home, and rail'd at his Quéen, ſaying, ſhe was a Whore, and what ſhe went withal was a Baſtard, and would not ſuffer her to come into his company: then this old Traytour went to the Quéen, pretending friendſhip under a falſehood, and adviſed her to go in a merry way and preſent the King a Bowl of Wine; and ſhe alwayes thinking he had been a moſt faithful friend did as he adviſed her, and before ſhe brought it, he wrote a Libel and dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt it in the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chamber: This Libel expreſſed, that if the Quéen at ſuch a time did preſent him with a Bowl of Wine, he was a dead man, for it was poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and as the Queen came in, with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent love, preſented the King with the Bowl of Wine, he took his foot and kickt it all down, ſaying, Thou wicked wretch, now I do perceive the vile actions, thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed
<pb facs="tcp:55822:57"/>my Bed, and defamed my Honour, and art thou now come to poiſon me, I ſwear thou ſhalt dye the cruelleſt death as may be thought on: ſo committed her to priſon, and as ſhe lay there ſhe breathed out theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Who e're thou art this Childe doth finde,</l>
                     <l>Make much of it to her prove kinde,</l>
                     <l>She mighty honour may thee-bring,</l>
                     <l>Being onely Daughter to a King;</l>
                     <l>Be tender, loving, then to ſhe,</l>
                     <l>One day thou ſhalt rewarded be.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>When the King heard this, he knew ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:55822:59"/>was his Daughter that he commanded to be thrown into the Sea, and ſaiv, ſines the Gods and Fortune has favoured her, I have no reaſon to hate her; therefore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her to be brought home to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and clothed her in moſt rich aray, and made her ſit at his right hand, after that, he diſpatch'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> four of his Noblemen to the I ſtand of <hi>Delphos,</hi> to inquire of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> whether the Queen was guilty of the charge laid againſt her, and when they came in the Temple before the Oracle, they did their reverence, and the Oracle ſpake, and ſaid, <hi>Stand here two dayes, and ſpeak not one word, and the third day you ſhall finde on the back ſide of the Oracle a ſcroll of Parchment ſealed up; that take and haſte away to the King, and break it not up till you come in the Judgement Hall, and before all the Councel, there the King ſhall finde the truth written;</hi> then they did their obeyſance, and ſo departed, and took ſhipping, and the ſeventh day they arrived in their own Countrey: when they came before the King, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him what the Oracle had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to do, and forth with the King aſſembled all his Lords into the Iudgment Hall, every one expecting a ſad doom for the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:60"/>Quéen; but when the Scroll was broke open, and read, it proved thus, ſaying, <hi>The Queen is innocent, her Childe is lawfully begotten, the old Counſellour is the Traytor; and the King ſhall dye without an Heir, if Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice takes not place.</hi> When the Counſel heard this, they all rejoyced, and the King ſent immediately for his Queen out of priſon, but the meſſenger brought him word again, that the Quéen was dead; then the King fell a weeping and wringing his hands, ſaying, O miſerable wretch am I, that believed ſuch an old curſed Caitiff as I have done! O woe is me that ever I was born, I caus'd my Child to be drown'd in the Sea, had not the Gods and Fortune pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd her, and now I have ſlain my vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and innocent Quéen by falſe and bitter impriſonment, through the advice of an old curſed Villain; ſurely he ſhall dye the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerableſt death as may be thought of: and ſpéedily he commanded two wilde Horſes to be brought, and ty'd the Traytors two hands to one tail, and his two legs to the other; ſo drew him limb from limb, and threw his quarters to the beaſts of the field and the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wles of the air, a juſt reward for ſuch an inhumane Traytor: And then he prepar'd
<pb facs="tcp:55822:60"/>the richeſt Tomb that ever was ſéen for his Quéen, and commanded all the Lords and Barons of the Land to appear at her great Funeral, which was ſolemnized in mighty ſtate, and honourably interr'd her in his own Chappel, where upon her Tomb he cauſed to be ingraven theſe words following.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Through ill advice of evil Traytors, I</l>
                     <l>Have ſlain my Queen in woful miſery;</l>
                     <l>For which advice I ever ſhall repent,</l>
                     <l>And to my dying day be diſcontent:</l>
                     <l>And whoſoe're thou art that paſſeth by,</l>
                     <l>Curſe him that caus'd thy Queen to dye.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Empreſs, you have ſhewed me a good Example to beware of had Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; therefore my Daughter ſhall not dye: And the Miſtris departed from her with a joyful heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſixth Complaint of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>WHen <hi>Radamentus</hi> perceiving by the muttering of the ſervants that the young Princeſs was repriev'd again, he grew ſo impatient, that all thought he would have run mad; therefore they ran and fold
<pb facs="tcp:55822:61"/>the Empreſs, that <hi>Radamentus</hi> was going beſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e himſelf, for they never ſaw him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch a paſſion: Then the Empreſs went to him and ſaid, wherefore my good Lord are you ſo impatient? he anſwered, O Lady, how ſhall I hide my grief I the great love I bear to you doth prohibit me from leaving you, and if I tray, I ſee nothing but ruine and deſtruction doth attend you, in ſuffering ſuch baſe and laſcivious actions, committed by your graceleſs Daughter, and not ſuppreſſed according to Law, that I am aſhamed to go out in the ſight of the ſun; my Counſel which you ought to receive you ſlight, and rather believe the old wives fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, then my grave Counſel: Therefore I fear it will happen to you worſe then it did to the Lady, who tender'd her young Lion above all ſhe had, till at the laſt he fore her throat, as is mentioned in the Example. O my good Lord ſaid the Empreſs, ſhew me that Example; and ſaid gladly that would I do, but it availeth nothing, to morrow you will hear the Miſtriſſes again, nevertheleſs I'e ſhew you one Example more, and began as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:61"/>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The ſixth Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>SOmetime in <hi>Aſia</hi> lived a Lady, who being with childe lunged for a young Lion, ſo that inquiſition was made all over <hi>Aſia</hi> for a young Lion; at laſt a Nobleman being a hunting in a wilde Forteſt, chanced to catch a Lyons whel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſent it to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who no ſooner receiv'd it, but fell in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and was delivered of a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, whom ſhe loved marvellouſly, and kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lion alwayes by her, feeding it with all the dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhe poſſible could get, and the Lion would follow her up and down the houſe, and ſeem'd as tame as a Dog: at laſt he would walk abroad, and run among the ſheep but meddle with none, that cauſed the Lady to love him, and tender him like as ſhe did a Childe, ſéeing he would run after her ſo pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily among the ſhéep, and not touch any; but why ſhould he, when his belly was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>'d with all the Dainties that may be got. But it came to paſs upon a time, the Lady want from home, and committed the charge of her young Lion to her maid, but alas ſhe gave him not the attendance her Lady did; wherefore he ran out among the Flock, and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:62"/>ſlew one of the beſt ſhéep therein, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouted him; when the Lady came home, the Shepheard complained to her, and ſaid, the Lion had ſlain one of the beſt ſhéep in the Flock, and the Lady would not believe it, till the Stoward came, and alſo verified it; then ſaid the Lady, alas, if he has ſlain one of the Flock, it is but through his fooliſhneſs, for he is but a whelp, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and knew not what he did, but if we catch him again doing ſuch a trick, we will correct him for it; and not long after he came into the Flock and ſlew two, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as much as he could, the reſt that was left a Greyhound of the houſe found and eat it; the Lion being come home firſt, and got to his Couch, there was no ſuſpition of him, but the poor Greyhound coming home with his chops all bloody, was apprehended of the Shepheard, and all the blame put upon him; wherefore the Lady commanded him to be hang'd, therefore according to the old Proverb, <hi>It is better for ſome to ſteal an horſe, then another to look over the hedge:</hi> The third time the Lion went to the Flock, ſlew thrée, and glutted himſelf in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>; then the Shepheard complained the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time, but could have no redreſs, the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:62"/>Lady ſtill pardoning him, hoping he would mend: and the fourth time he fell among the Flock, ſlaying and ſpoiling above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; then all people cry'd ſhame upon the Lady, for kéeping a ravenous Beaſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſo good a Flock; yet the Lady would not kill him, nor hardly give credit to what they ſaid, nevertheleſs ſhe kept him in her Chamber cloſe for two or thrée dayes, and he lay cloſe by the Cradle where her young Son was; and it happened one morning
<figure/> one morning, that his wrath began to riſe, and his eyes ſéemed as red as blood, walking up and down the Chamber, he ſmelt to the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:63"/>Cradle where the Infant lay, and at laſt jumpt upon him, and fore him all to pieces, and eat him before the mothers face; then the Lady wrung her hands, and curſt the time ſhe refuſed to kill him: but that did not ſatisfie the ſavage beaſt, but after he had diſpatcht the Childe, he jumpt upon the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and fore her joynt from joynt; and when the ſervants ran up and lookt through the key hole, all the Chamber was of a gore blood.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> I fear it will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to you as it did unto this poor Lady, in tendering and ſaving your wicked Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo oft, that when ſhe comes to have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhe will deſtroy your Subjects the good Sheep, and after bring you to a miſerable end. Then ſaid the Empreſs, ſurely that ſhall not be, for to morrow my Daughter ſhall dye: then ſhe commanded her Officers to lead her away to the ſtake, arrayed all over in a white rove ſignifying Death: then all the people cry'd out, alas, and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more! the Empreſs Daughter is leading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to dye, &amp; they much lamented her death. Then the ſixth Miſtris when ſhe heard of it, mounted on horſeback, and haſted to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; who was no ſooner come, but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb facs="tcp:55822:63"/>diſdainfully lookt upon her, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her ſorely that ſhe ſhould dye with her Daughter, for bringing her up in ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid actions, that all the world was aſham'd of her: The Miſtris ſaid, I have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd as you ſay; and as for your Daughter you ſhall know ſhe ſhall ſpeak within three dayes, and all the truth ſhall come to light; but if you put her to death for the words of one man, it will ſurely happen to you as it rid to the Princeſs of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> who for the love of a foreign Prince, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of an evil Counſellour, cauſed her own precious Daughter to be put to death, for which after ſhe would have given her own life. For the love of God ſaid the Empreſs, ſhew me that Example; that ſhall I not do ſaid the Miſtris, except you ſend for your Daughter back again, otherwiſe ſhe may be dead, and then I ſhould talk to you in vain: Then the Empreſs commanded her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be call'd back again; and the Miſtris began as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the ſixth Miſtris.</head>
                  <p>SOme time in <hi>Burgundy</hi> lived a fair Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of famous worth and great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:64"/>this Princeſs took wonderful great delight in ſeeing Juſts and Turnies: where upon a time there came ſeveral brave Princes and Nobles to ſhew their valour before this great Princeſs, and there aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeventy and thrée brave Heroes, and when the Princeſs baheld them all, ſhe thought the magnificency of the whole world were that day aſſembled together: amongſt whom was valiant <hi>Brutus,</hi> one of the Knights of <hi>Malts;</hi> and he behad'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo valſantly, that all the honour of the day accrewed to him, that the Princeſs was ſo much enamoured on him, that her eye was fixed all day long upon the place where he ſtood; and when the day was over, this valiant <hi>Brutus</hi> came off the Field with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umpets ſounding, and victorious Trophies bore before him: Now the Lady was in the window of her Caſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all the while, and beheld his worthy acts, ſo that her love burned on him, but could not tell how to reveal it: Yet afterwards ſhe invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Knight to a Banquet, and ſent the maſſage by her own Steward, for which <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> returned the Princeſs many thanks, and reputed her invitation as a great honour; and when the Day was come, the Knight
<pb facs="tcp:55822:64"/>
                     <figure/> appeared before the Princeſs in ſuch a brave geſture and comely deportment, that the Princeſs was raviſht to ſee the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his carriage; ſo they went to Dinnex that day, and paſſed away the time in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental diſcouries: Now this Lady had a Daughter moſt beaufiful and fair, full of modeſty and vertue, and of comoly ſeatures, and upon her the Knight had a fixed eye, but the Princeſs never minded that, for ſhe thought the Knight was more ambitions to Court her then her Daughter, being young and of tenver years, therefore ſhe was clear of any fealonſie of her Daughter: ſo after
<pb facs="tcp:55822:65"/>they had feaſted together for the ſpace of a wéek, the Knight moſt courteouſly took his leave of the Princeſs, and departed home into his own Countrey, promiſing to come again ſoon after; but failing to come, the Lady wondering the Knight did not come, ſhe askt her Steward what may be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it? he ſaid, that he perceived the ſight of her little Hound did diſpleaſe him, therefore he would not come; now this Princeſs loved the Hound as ſhe did the greateſt Jewel ſhe had, nevertheleſs by the Stewards advice ſhe commanded him to be put to death. Now, ſaid ſhe, I hope I ſhall pleaſe the Knight when he comes; ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Knight came, and courted the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs very highly, but as he was coming through a dark room in the Caſtle, he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſtumble; and he ſaid to himſelf, Ile never come this way again: the Princeſs hearing the Knight ſay ſo, asked the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward why he ſaid ſo? quoth he, becauſe the Parret was in that room; O ſaid the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, though I prize the Parret as my life, yet go and kill it: So after they had peſſed the time away in all Courtly Delights and Princely Sports for the ſpace of a whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>th together, the Knight moſt courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb facs="tcp:55822:65"/>took his leave of the Princeſs, and went again into his own Countrey, for his affections were altogether knit upon the young Lady, though he bid it in obſcurity, &amp; the Princeſs thought it was upon her ſelf, ſo the time paſſed beyond her expectation in looking for the Knights coming again, and admiring at his abſence ſo long, asked her Steward what might be the reaſon of it, of whom ſhe alwayes took advice? and he ſaid, the Knight has more love for the young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy your Daughter, then he has to you; for alwayes when he is here, ſhe is in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber wantonly playing with him, and ſhe does all what ſhe can to conſpire your Death; and if ſhe live any longer, ſhe will prove to be your utter ruins and deſtruction. Then the Princeſs commanded her to be ſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed upon the Altar to the Oracle of <hi>Apollo;</hi> then there was an Altar erected before the Palace Gate, covered all over with black, upon which was placed four great War-Candles ſet in ſockets of ſilver, by which was placed a Block of Ebony, a Chaſing-diſh of Coles, and a Knite for the Eracuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner: Theſe being ready, the young Lady was brought upon the Altar, attended by twelve Ladies arrayed all in white Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:66"/>then the dying Lady ſpake to the Princeſs as followeth: <hi>Moſt reverend Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and dread Princeſs, I am here brought to be ſacrificed for things laid to my Charge I know not of; and if you put me to death, there is a God of all things who knoweth the ſecrets of all mens hearts, that will in one day bring the truth to light, to the ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of the unjuſt, who are guilty of this my innocent Death.</hi> And thus having ended her Speech, and preparing for the Block, <hi>Brutus</hi> the valiant Knight ruſhed into the Palace pard, who demanded the cauſe of the multitude, and the people ſaid, that the Princeſs Daughter that day was to be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed; then the Knight ſpurred his Stéed, and rote among the people, making a lane which way he came, and reſcued the Lady from the Altar, and brought her in before her mother again; and ſaid to the Princeſs, Madam, you had but thrée things in your Palace beſide your ſelf, which I delighted in, and thoſe you would deſtroy: The Princeſs asked him which were thoſe? and the Knight ſaid, Your Daughter, your Hound: and your Parret, and the Princeſs ſaid, My Steward informed me the Hermd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſſend you, and addiſed me to kill him,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:66"/>and another time told me the Parret diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed you, and counſelled me to deſtroy it, and thirdly, my Daughter had moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly conſpired my death, for which he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed me to ſacrifice her to the Oracle of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Then ſaid the Knight, call hither the Steward, who being come, he asked him, did I tell thee the Hound offended me? he ſaid no: he asked him again, did I tell thee the Parret diſpleaſed me? and he ſaid no: didſt thou ever ſée the Lady in my Chamber? and he anſwered nothing, but fell down upon his knées, and begg'd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of the Princeſs. Then ſaid the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, O curſed Traytor, what haſt thou made me to de, ſo ſlay my Hound I loved ſo dearly, and the Parret as I did my life, and to attempt the murther of my onely Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, through thy treacherous, baſe, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Counſel; ſurely thou ſhalt dys f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo commanded him to be led to the Gallows and hang'd: Thus was the vertuous Lady ſaved, and the unjuſt Traytor condemned. Now ſaid the Miſtris, underſtand ye what I have ſaid? yes right well ſaid the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and it rejoyceth my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rt the young Lady was ſaved; therefore my Daughter this day ſhall not dye: Then ſaid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:67"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you do to you will do well; therefore I commend you to God, and thank you for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Daughter this day for my ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſeventh Complaint of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>WHen <hi>Radamentus</hi> beard the young Lady was pardoned again, he ran up and down the Garden like a mad man, cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing with a loud voice, O unhappy man am I that ſhould thus come into this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, pretending to execute juſtice, and I am conſtrained to ſuffer vice to be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to the ruine of the Empreſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Empire, and ſhame and confuſion to my own felf; I wiſh I ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come here! and the Empreſs ſaid, leave off ſuch talk, Iuſtice ſhall be done. O La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> it will happen to you as it did to the Queen of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> which is mentioned in the Example; good my Lord ſaid the Empreſs, ſhew me that Example; that I will gladly do ſaid <hi>Radamentus,</hi> if you with take example by it, otherwiſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th me nothing to tell it you, for I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you ſix already, and yet you are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ded from them by ſix fooliſh women; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>leſs I will ſhew you this one,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:67"/>though it be the laſt I eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall do.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The ſeventh Example of Radamentus.</head>
                  <p>THere was a Quéen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>? the <hi>Vandals</hi> upon a time who had a very beautifull Daughter, who ſhe tendered very much, and loved as ſhe did her own life; inſomuch, that whereſoever ſhe went, her Daughter muſt go along with her; and as they were walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a time in the fields, the young Lady had a Bird in her hand, whom ſhe
<figure/> would very fain have to ſing and becauſe ſhe could not make him ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g, the pecke out his
<pb facs="tcp:55822:68"/>two eyes with her Bookin, and turn'd it looſe, and the Bird flew back, and by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent lichted in the branch of a Vine which grew over the Queens window, and there hardented for a while ſinging very doleful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every morning at the Queens window: Then ſaid the Queen, O that I knew but what this poor Bird doth ſo mournfully ſing now his eyes be out? And then ſtood up an old man whoſe name was <hi>Mimnon,</hi> and ſaid, if it may not offend the Queen, I ſhall declare the interpretation of the Song: then ſaid the Queen, ſpeak on; and he ſaid, Gracious Lady, the contents of the ſong is a warning to you to beware and to cut off. The interpretation is, to beware that your Daughter peck not out your eyes as ſhe did his; and that you cut her off before ſhe come to that maturity, as to ſit upon your Throne with the Crown upon her head, when you are on the pavement on your bare knees. And the Quéen anſwered, theſe are but fables, believe them not, my dear childe is of no ſuch nature: ſo paſt it over like the old ſaying, till the time of repentance was too late; for ſhe tender'd her Daughter ſo much, that ſhe would make her Queen to rule one your, and her ſelf another, and did
<pb facs="tcp:55822:68"/>ratifie and confirm by her own hand and Seal, that whatſoever her Daughter did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act or do in her Reign, it ſhould ſtand as law for ever eſtabliſhed; ſo when her Daughter came to maturity the Quéen would néeds ſée how the Crown would become her, and made her Daughter Quéen for that year, and Crowned her in great pomp: when her Daughter had on the Royal Robe and Crown, and all the power in her own hands, ſhe thought it became her ſo well, that ſhe was loath to part with it; and for to kéep it while ſhe had it, that very year ſhe tart her Mother, the late Quéen of high Treaſon for the death of her Father, and brought her upon her knees before the Bar of Iuſtice, and ſhe ſate upon the Royal Throne. The Quéen perceiving her Daughters tyranny began to ſpring aloſt, the night following ſhe made her eſcape, thinking to raiſe an Army; but her Daughter being too cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, laid watch and ward round the City and took her again, and to prevent her fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eſcape, boared both her eyes out, and then the Queen remembred the ſinging of the poor blinde Bird, and wept moſt bitterly, ſaying, Curſed be the time that I refuſed to obey the voice of the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:69"/>Bird; after that this wicked Daughter brought her again to the Bar of Iuſtice, and ſound her guilty for endeavouring her eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, that in one day ſhe depoſed her of Life, Crown, and Kingdom, and after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eigned a wicked Tyrant, that all people cuſt the day ſhe was born: therefore I fear your wicked Daughter will prove ſo to you if you let her live. The Empreſs ſaid, God forbid it ſhould happen ſo; but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, to morrow I ſhall ſit in Iudgement, and ſhe ſhall ſurely dye: and on the morrow ſhe commanded her Officers to lead her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the ſtake. When <hi>Penthiſila</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Miſtriſs heard that, away ſhe haſted to the Empreſs, and did her obeyſance, and the Empreſs frowningly lookt upon her, and ſaid, O thou curſed Caitif, what haſt thou done to my childe, how haſt thou taught her to be a Whore, a Beaſt, and a Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and alſo haſt cut the tongue out of her head that ſhe cannot ſpeak? thou ſhalt dye as well as ſhe, for I long to be avenged on thee and all the fellows. Then ſaid <hi>Penthiſila,</hi> Moſt gracious Empreſs, the accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your vertuous Daughter is fulſe, and it is but a ſmall time betwixt this and to morrow noon, and if you pleaſe to ſpare her
<pb facs="tcp:55822:69"/>till then, with the help of Almighty God ſhe ſhall ſpeak unto you in all vertuous learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the truth of all things ſhall be made manifeſt; but if you will not, it ſhall, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to you as it did unto a rich widow which is mentioned in the Example. Then ſhew me that Example, ſaid the Empreſs, that ſhall I not do, ſaid the Miſtris, except you call your Daughter gain; then ſhall you hear ſuch a notable Example, as you ſhall beware the advice of one man as long as you live, and ſo began as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of the ſeventh Miſtris.</head>
                  <p>UPon a time there was a mighty rich Widow who had a bountiful Eſtate, and ſhe had one onely Daughter, who was Heireſs unto this Eſtate; but it chanced that this Widow being not capable altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to govern it all, ſhe choſe a grave Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to be her aſſiſtant in the government of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Now ſaid this old man, if I could cut off the Heireſs, I would quickly iuggle the Widow out of it, and then rule as chief Lord my ſelf in it: And to begin his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, he ſaid to the Widow, I hold it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry convenient, ſince you are a Widow and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:70"/>I a Batchelor, to conclude a Marriage and ſpend our dayes together, provided that you will cut off the intail, and diſinberit your Daughter, whereby we may injoy it while we do live, and after our deceaſe we will give it to her again. The Widow lik't this very well, thinking he had adviſed her to the beſt, and thereupon diſinherited her own childe: then ſhe asked the old man to be as good as his promiſe, who ſaid, I will marry ye if you will aſſign the whole Eſtate over to me, then I will marry ye on <hi>May</hi> day next, and be careful of your childe, loving to you, and govern it all. Then the Widow hearing that, repoſed great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, made all her Eſtate over to him: When this was done, he neither look't after the Childe nor cared for the Widow, which made the Daughter run di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, and dyed in the publick Field, and at <hi>May</hi> day the Widow wondered why he would not come and perform his promiſe, at laſt went to him, and ask't him, Sir, why do you not perform your promiſe, and marry me? why, ſaid the old Miniſter, I am ready to marry ye if you have got a good Husband: ſten ſaid the Widow, Will not you be my Husband? no, ſaid he, I promiſed but to
<pb facs="tcp:55822:70"/>marry ye, not to be your Husband; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier knave you, then, ſaid the Widow; ſo the went out and wept bitterly, ſaying, That band which ſigned all my Eſtate to youder curſed Caitif from my own Childe, ſhall now end my miſerable life, ſo ſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> het ſelf. Then ſaid the Miſtris, underſtand ye Madam what I have ſaid, yes, right well ſaid the Empreſs: then ſaid the Miſtris, beware, and believe not that old Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, for he does but labour to cut off your onely Daughter, and after to ruins you, ſo 07 that he may reign as Lord and Emperour. You have ſhewed me a good Example, ſaid the Empreſs, though it grieves my heart to hear it proved ſo fatal to the Widow; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Daughter ſhall not dye this day, but I ſhall rejoyce exceedingly to hear her ſpeak to morrow: ſaid the Miſtris, by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Divine Powers ſhe ſhall ſpeak, whereby ſhe ſhall decide all the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances betwixt <hi>Radamentus</hi> and us, and you ſhall ſee the truth brought to light, ſo took leave of the Empreſs, and departed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:55822:71"/>
               <head>Chap. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">How Sabrina the Empreſs Daughter complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Radamentus, and how ſhe excuſed her ſelf of her accuſation.</head>
               <p>NOw all the Miſtriſſes, <hi>Penthiſila, Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cere, Dejanara, Boadicia, Mardula,</hi> and <hi>Halicuja</hi> took counſel how they ſhould bring the Princeſs out of Priſon to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; ſo they went to the Princeſs on the morrow betimes to counſel her, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſaid, take no care what I ſhall ſay, I am provided already: then they all rejoyced, and clothed her in cloth of Gold, and put her in a Chariot, drawn by ſix milk white Stéed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and they rid on horſeback, three be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Chariot, one of each ſide, and two behinde, with ſtately Banners carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and all ſorts of Muſick playing; when the Empreſs heard the noiſe ſhe aſked what it meant, and the people ſaid, the young Princeſs and all the ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſas <hi>of Rome</hi> were coming to the Palace; and the Empreſs rejoyced exceedingly, and came cut to meet them, and when the Princeſs was come, ſhe ſaid to her Mother, Hall my moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mother, and fell upon
<pb facs="tcp:55822:71"/>her knees, and the Empreſs full of joy to hour her ſpeak, took her up in her arms and kiſt her: then began the Princeſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the whole matter before the Empreſs, and all the whole multitude, and ſhe began as followeth, Moſt dear Mother, before I procéed, I deſire that my accuſer <hi>Radamentus</hi> and all the Gentlemen of his Bed-Chamber do appear before us; ſo the Empreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Radamentus</hi> to appear with all his men, who immediately came: then ſaid the Princeſs, Moſt dear Mother, behold the
<figure/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:72"/>young Gentleman that ſtandeth there in black, who is favourite to <hi>Radamentus,</hi> above all others. command him to be ſtript before us all: ſaid the Empreſs, that will be a ſhame to us? nay ſaid the Princeſs, be the ſhame to theſe that deſerve it; and when be was unclothed he was known to be a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the admiration of all.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Complaint of the Princeſs againſt Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentus.</head>
                  <p>THen ſaid the Princeſs to her Mother, behold this Fornicator and this Whore, who bath commonly lain with him in his bed, committing the foul ſin of fornication; which thing he would alſo have committed with me in the Garden, and becauſe I would not conſent to his filthy luſt, he ran out, crying, he had ſeen me lying with a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Fig tree, and thereby complained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly againſt me ſeeking all poſſible means how to take my life away: Therefore moſt gracious Mother, give me leave to reprove him of all his grievous ſlanders, and falſe accuſations, word by word; and I beſéech you to hear me patiently. When you ſent for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> at his requeſt, I beheld the Stars, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:72"/>which I knew, that if I ſhould have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> any other, within ſeven dayes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ld are a ſhameful death, for which cauſe I did forbear to ſpeak until this preſent. When the Empreſs heard her Daughter ſo juſt and learnedly vindicate the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth, ſhe ſaid to <hi>Radamentus,</hi> O wicked wretch, was not thy Concubine enough to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy faul and lecherous appoſite, but wouldſt have had to do with my onely Daughter. Then <hi>Radamentus</hi> fell to the gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd and begg'd pardon; but the Empreſs ſaid, O ungratsful Traytor, thou doſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mercy, but thou ſhalt finde none, for the law ſhall be upon thee even unto a ſhameful death as thou haſt deſerved.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Princeſs, Moſt gracious Mother, it was told you by this wretched Caitiff, that I ſhould by the help of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſes, endeavour your deſtruction, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Government to my ſelf? Alas, I ſhould more rather uſe all the art and skill I have to help and ſupport you in all your Government about your Empire, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute you my Sovereign, ſince I have from you all my living and maintenance, not to deprive you of your Dignity, for in your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour do I glory. Then ſaid the Empreſs.
<pb facs="tcp:55822:73"/>bleſſed be Almighty God, that I have ſuch a good and learned Daughter, that I finde ſo expert in all Arts and Sciences; therefore declare to me one example whereby I may underſtand thy wiſdome perfectly, then ſhall I have ioy of thee, and my heart will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. Then ſaid the Princeſs, Gracious Mother, Command ſilence among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that all may hear me, and when I have ended, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ſentence according to law upon me and <hi>Radamentus:</hi> When the Hall was ſilenced, the Princeſs began as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="story">
                  <head>The Example of Sabrina the Empreſs Daughter.</head>
                  <p>THere was a Queen which had but one Daughter, whom ſhe loved as ſhe did her life; therefore the Queen delivered her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Wiſe Miſtris to be brought up, and be inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>d in all vertuous Learning and Wiſdom: and when ſhe had béen with her Miſtris a certain while, her Mother had a deſire to ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, and ſent Letters to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris to bring home her Daughter; when ſhe came, ſhe appeared to her Mother, ſo expert in learning, comely in behaviour, and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto all, that the Queen rejoyced ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedingly: and it happened on a time, as ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:55822:73"/>delivered a bowl of Wine to her Mother, the Queen looked upon the wall and ſaw the ſhadow of a hand which wrote three lines in an unknown tongue, and the Quéen began to fear greatly, and ſaid, happy were that perſon which could interpret what that wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting meant; then her Daughter ſaid, if it may not offend the Quéen, I could give the true interpretation thereof: and the Quéen ſaid, ſpeak on my good Daughter; and the Childe ſaid, Moſt honoured Mother, this writing doth ſignifie, that I ſhall become a mighty Princeſs, and ſhall be honoured of all people, eſpecially my own Mother, who ſhall bring me a Bowl of Wine, and bow thrée times, and knéel in the delivery of it; and the Queen ſaid, Thou ſhalt never be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured ſo of me, nor have ſuch ſervice; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe commanded her ſervants to take her into a Foreſt far from the Court, and there ſlay her, and bring her Heart to ſhew her, that ſhe may know the truth of her death: ſo the ſervants took her away to the Foreſt, and having compaſſion on ſo ſweet a Childe, ſaid among themſelves, let us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Queen in this bloody <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſave the Childe, and we will put her in this hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Tree, and kill a Lamb of the Mountain
<pb facs="tcp:55822:74"/>and bring the Heart to the Queen, which accordingly they did, and the Queen belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it was the Heart of her Daughter: ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Prophecies ſometime prove not true. And it chanced that on the morrow after, a ſtrange Knight hapned to hunt in the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, where the Childe was to be ſlain, and his Dogs beyed about the tree, where the Queens Daughter was: at laſt the Knight looked in the hollow of the tree, and there he eſpied a young Girle of ſuch incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beauty, that his eyes never beheld a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, which made him ſuſpect that ſhe was of ſome noble race; and ſo he commanded his ſervants to be careful of her, and to bring her into his own countrey, where he did bring her up in all learned Arts, and with royal attendants, till at laſt her fame began to ring throughout the whole Kingdome, for Vertue, Beauty and Learning; and the Emperour of that Land being very youthful, came to that Knights houſe for ſo view her. And no ſooner did he behold her, but he was ſmitten with the inflamation of Love, and after dinner he danced with her, and in the evening he married her, and brought her in great triumph and ſolemnity home to his own Court. And after that, the thrée Eaſtern
<pb facs="tcp:55822:74"/>Kings hearing of her fame, came to ſee her beauty, and to bring her preſents: thus for thrée years ſhe lived with her husband the Emperour in all joy and happineſs, and then he dyed, leaving the whole Empire unto
<figure/> ſhe, who was then called the great Empreſs of <hi>Blodermario.</hi> When ſhe was thus in the height of all her glory, ſhe viewed the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, and perceived by her skill in Aſtrology, how her Mother that day was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Prince of <hi>Moravia,</hi> of Crown and Kingdom, and baniſhed out of her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and laying to heart the diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:55822:75"/>her mother was in, had compaſſion on her, (for pure Nature will never fall away) and therefore ſhe raiſed a brave and mighty Army, and marched towards her mothers Countrey: which newes did ſlye before her, that it was told the Queen her mother, the great Empreſs of <hi>Blodermario</hi> was coming to her aſſiſtance; which made the Queen to rejoyce, and wonder greatly, knowing ſhe had never no correſpondency with her before. Wherefore ſhe went to meet her, and when ſhe came before the great Empreſs, ſhe fell down upon her knees, and ſaid O great Empreſs, how have I meritted ſo great honour and favour, that your m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt Excellent Majeſty have vouchſafed to come in perſon, and eſtabliſh me again in my kingdom! Then the Empreſs took her up, and have her come in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the Chariot to her, and when they came home to the Court, the Queen brought the Empreſs a bowl of wine and bowed three times, and fell down upon her knees to preſent it: then the Empreſs commanded her ſervants to depart the room, and then ſhe asked the Queen what Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhe had; and the Queen anſwered, ſhe had one Daughter but ſhe was dead. Then the Empreſs ſaid, tell me true, did ſhe dye a
<pb facs="tcp:55822:75"/>natural death or no: tell me the truth, for I ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by my Crown you ſhall come to no dammage. Then the Quéen anſwered, Moſt glorious Princeſs, I brought up my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in all vertuous Learning, Arts and Sciences, that for her wiſdom and comely behaviour ſhe was honoured of all people, and beloved of every one; ſhe was my onely delight, and in her abſence was my greateſt ſorrow, that without her preſence I was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content: when I was wont to ſit down to meals, ſhe was alwayes at my elbow, to give me a bowle of wine when I ſhould pleaſe to call for it; for the pleaſanteſt draught that ever I drank was out of her hand. And it happened upon a time as I ſats at dinner, my Daughter waited upon me, and as ſhe bare a bowle of wine to my hand, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared the ſhadow of an Arm upon the wall, and it wrote three lines to the great aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of us all: and I beheld it my ſelf, and ſaid, That perſon was happy which could read and interpret thoſe Lines that were written upon the wall by a ſecret and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known band, that none but the Diverts pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did know of. Having thus ſpoken, my Daughter ſtood up and ſpake unto me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> words, If it may pleaſe my moſt dear
<pb facs="tcp:55822:76"/>and reverend mother not to be offended with me, I could read thoſe Lines upon the wall and interpret them, and give you the true meaning thereof. Then I anſwered and ſaid, Speak on my Daughter, and you ſhall finde whether I ſhall be angry or no: them my Daughter ſtood up boldly and ſaid, The Lines upon the wall written are in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Languages, but the interpretation doth predict or ſignifie, that I ſhall become a mighty Princeſs, and be honoured by all people, eſpecially by my own Parents; for the time ſhall come, that my Mother ſhall preſent a bowls of wine to me, and bow thrée times, and deliver it upon her knees. When the young Lady had thus made an end of declaring the interpretation of the Lines that were written upon the wall, her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was very wroth, and ſaid to her ſelf thus, I will never be ſo ſerviceable to my own daughter ſurely; and being in my fury I called my ſervants and commanded them to take her privately away, and conveigh her to the Foreſt of <hi>Bazar,</hi> and there deſtroy her; and for ſatisfaction thereof, to bring her Heart and ſhew it unto me, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly was done, and ſhe is dead; which for the reaſon you have heard I did deſtroy her.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:76"/>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Empreſs, you might well think it was much in vain to ſtrive againſt tho determinations of the holy will of God; for now you ſhall know of truth that what is decréed in Heaven above the force of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals can never fruſtrate below upon the earth; therefore be it known to you that I am your daughter whom you ſuppoſe to have been dead, and by the Providence of God I have been preſerved, the Lord putting it into the hearts of your ſervants not to ſlay me, but to put me into a hollow trée, where a Knight chanced to come that way a hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his Dogs did run and encompaſſed the ſaid trée round about howling and crying, whereby the Knight looking in to ſée what the reaſon was of his Dogs making ſuch a howling, he there found me: the ſervants alſo to ſatisfie your implacable wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, that you commanded to bring my Heart, to let you ſée the Execution was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, they ſlew a Lamb on the ſide of the mountain and preſented the Heart to you. The good Knight alſo that found me in the tree cartied me into his own Countrey, and preſented me to the Emperour, where I was not long before I was eſpouſed to him his Wiſe, and advanced to the Royal dignity of
<pb facs="tcp:55822:77"/>an Empreſs; and his moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſoon after deceaſed, and left me ſole Heir to his Empire, in which Honour and Glory I now remain. The Queen hearing theſe words, being raviſhed with ſoy, and all amazed, ſell down to the earth in a ſwound, whom the Empreſs loving, took up in her arms, ſaying, Now you ſhall know that my exaltation and dignity accrew to your glory, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, and profit, ſo they kiſt each other: then the Quéen began to weep, but the Empreſs ſaid Weep not my moſt dear and reverend mother, for you are reſtored to your Crown and Kingdom, whereby you ſhall be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all people above me during my life and reign. And afterwards there was a great Feaſt prepared, and all the Nobles and Barons of the Land aſſembled together to congratulate and joy with the young Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, in magnificent Shewes and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. After the great Day was over, and the Celebration ended, the young Empreſs ſent her Heraulds throughout all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to the Dukes and Princes to repair to her Mothers Royal Standard, and render their duty and obedience to her Majeſty, and to ſet the Crown again upon her Head. And after ſhe had ſettled her mother in a firme
<pb facs="tcp:55822:77"/>and flouriſhing peace, ſhe departed in great honour and glory, and returned into her own Empire.</p>
                  <div type="lesson">
                     <head>Here follows the Application of the Example.</head>
                     <p>THen ſaid <hi>Sabrina</hi> to the Empreſs her mother, Vnderſtand you Madam what I have ſaid? Yes right well ſaid the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. Then ſaid the daughter, Moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy mother, though God hath endued me with Learning and Wiſdom ſo far abode others, yet it ſhall rather be applied to the ſupporting of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Honour and Dignity, then to the impairing of your glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: like as the great Empreſs in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry height of all her Honour, though former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her mother did ſeek her deſtruction, ſhe did not infringe her mothers Prerogative, but on the contrary, ſhe helped her and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged her Dominions. Nay, when her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was baniſht from her Realm, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd her again to her Kingdom, and put the Royal Diadem upon her head; and by her great ſtrength and potent power, cauſed all the bordering Princes round about to live in fear of her moſt Excellent Majeſty.
<pb facs="tcp:55822:78"/>And as long as the Empreſs lived, her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was honoured above her, and enjoyed her Kingdoms in a flouriſhing peace and tranquillity. Then the Empreſs took her daughter by the hand and led her up to the upper and of the Hall, and placed her in a Chair of State upon her right hand; then ſhe aſſembled all her Nobles and Barons, and Privy Councellours, both Ladies and Gentlewoman, and before them all ſpake thus to her daughter.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>Then after the Empreſs had ended her ſpeech, all the Lords of the Councel ſtood up and ſaid, Moſt gracious Empreſs, we do all think our ſelves happy this day, that it hath pleaſed your moſt Excellent Majeſty to declare ſo much your will and pleaſure unto us; far be it from the heart of any of your noble Subjects this day here preſent, to derogate or diſanul the leaſt tittle what your Majeſties moſt gracious pleaſure is, but as willingly do ratifie, confirm, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh every word and ſyllable contained therein, as willingly as ever we plac't the Royal Diadem upon your head: and we do here unanimouſly, and with a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, firſt, with your gracious leave and ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſure, we do ordain and acknowledge, the Princeſs your Daughter to be our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb facs="tcp:55822:79"/>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dy and Empreſs. And furthermore we do ordain and appoint the ninth day of the ſecond Moneth, to be Celebrated for the Day of her Coronation.</p>
                     <p>And when all things were ready and the day come, all the Nobles of the Land ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that day in their Robes; the old Empreſs rode before upon a pavilion drawn be ſir Horſes, and two led on each ſide the Pavilion in cloth of State: four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tropbies or Banners were carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Next came the young elected Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in an open Chariot drawn by twelve Camels covered with cloth of Silver all in State, and the Banner Royal was carried before the Empreſs Chariot, with Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets founting, and all ſorts of Muſick plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughout all the City up to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, where the young Empreſs alighted out of her Chariot, and walked up to the Royal Throne guarded by her Nobles, and with a rich Canopy bore over her head. When ſhe came into the great Hall, ſhe aſcended up to the Royal Throne; then after the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were ended, the Nobles put the Crown upon her Head, and the Scepter in her Hand, and before the old Empreſs ſwore their Alegiance to the young Empreſs: and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:80"/>then with great Joy and Acclamations, the people ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d and ſaid, God ſave the new Empreſs.</p>
                     <p>Then was the old Empreſs brought into the Hall, where great Ceremonies and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence was done to her; then ſhe aſcended up to the Royal Throne, and placed ſhe was by the young Empreſs upon her left hand, and the young Empreſs began to ſpeak to her mother in this manner:</p>
                     <p>Moſt glorious and loving mother, it hath been your will and pleaſurs to confer upon me this Royal Dignity before your deceaſe, not my Ambition to beſtre it: but though I fit in the Glorious Chair of this Empire, and Govern the People now in your Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time; yet moſt dear mother, the Name and Authority ſhall not depart from you as long as you live: but in all buſineſſes of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that doth belong to the State, I mean theſe great Concernments that be moſt painful and laborious, to eaſe you thereof, I will take the pains in admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring all helps and ſervices that in me li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as it becometh a loyal and faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra, according to my bounden duty.</p>
                     <p>When all the Nobles and Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors heard theſe worthy and Heroick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb facs="tcp:55822:80"/>of their young eleven Princeſs, they ſhould all again, and gave thanks to the Divine Powers for raiſing them up ſuch a vertuous and able Governour as ſhe, who was the Supporter of her mothers h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue Maintainer of the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws and Priviledges, and the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all the Realm. Where now we will leude her in her full power and Magiſtracy, proſecuting the falſe Iudge, evil Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and perſur'd and arrand Traitor, Rada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentus.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How Judgement was given upon Radamentus and his Concubine, and how they were both put to death.</head>
                  <p>NOw when the Empreſs had Crowned her Daughter, and all the great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity ended, ſhe called a Councel and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled there the Nobles, the Barons, and the Learned Iudges of the Land, for the ſpeedy tryal of <hi>Radamentus</hi> and his notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Concubins: and when they were all met together, and aſſembled in the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Hall, the Empreſs and her Mother being plac'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon the Royal Throne, and the Court ſate, Proclamation was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:81"/>and <hi>Radamentus</hi> ſent for; where immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he and his Concubine were brought into the Hall, faſt bound with cords, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſtand before the Bar. Then <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brina</hi> the young Empreſs ſtood up, and in a moſt Eloquent and Learned Spéech ſhe ſaid thus as followeth:</p>
                  <p>My Lords and Gentlemen of this honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Senate, and alſo all you moſt grave and reverend Iudges of the Land, you have beard already and are very ſenſible for what <hi>Radamentus</hi> and his Concubine, both now Priſoners at the Bar of Iuſtice, ſtand here indicted for. They are not brought hither for a Crime laid againſt them to take away their Lives wrongfully; but for a fact which they have committed in the higheſt degrée of inſclency, and that you very well all do know. And be it known, that when I was at School with the Seven Wiſe Miſtriſſes, (I may ſay of the world) and in the full pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of my Learning, this <hi>Radamentus</hi> now priſoner at the Bar, being then a very great Councellor to her Grace the Quéen my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as you all do know, did inſtigate my mother to ſend for me home, to the intent he might learn and finde out a way how to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap me, whereby to take away my life: and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:81"/>to effect his horrid Couſpiracy, he falſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my mother the Empreſs, that he ſaw me in the Palace Garden committing the foul ſin of Fornication, ſuppoſing that I could ſpeak and anſwer for my ſelf: and hereupon he brought ſeven Examples to my mother the Empreſs againſt me; and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very much for ſeven dayes together, to animate my mother againſt me. And the reaſon why I did not ſpeak within the time of thoſe ſeven dayes was, becauſe when my mother ſent for me through his inſtigation, I ſaw in the Planets a Fate which did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict a ſad omen to me: which was, that when I came to Court, if I did ſpeak a word within ſeven dayes, I ſhould be moſt miſerable, and be put to the moſt ſhameful death that ever Virgin was. Therefore to prevent his wicked intention, I did conceal my Spéech for ſo long; in which time my ſeven Wiſe Miſtriſſes by their learned skill and good diſcretion did labour in my behalf, and ſpake for me; each Miſtris ſpake by turn each day, and by Providence ſaved me: and the eighth day, by the aſſiſtance of the Divine Powers, I ſpake and anſwered for my ſelf; confuting all the ſhamefull and
<pb facs="tcp:55822:82"/>wicked accuſations this helliſh Monſter of mankinde had contrided againſt me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the unjuſtneſs of his own cauſe hath now heaped vengeance upon his own head: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Priſoner at the bar, in the time of my accuſation, and long before, did keep a private Concubine inſtead of a young man to wait on him, cloathed in mans apparel, to ſatisfie his own laſcivious luſt, and filthy appetite, and charged me an innocent Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with all thoſe abominable vices and wicked ſins, that he himſelf daily commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his ſecret chamber; he cauſed me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dayes one after another to be led to the Iudgement Hall, where there he ſate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and gave ſentence upon me, and cauſed me to be led to the Gallows ſhamefully to be burnt at a ſtake, for crimes laid againſt me that I was innocent of: Therefore moſt gracious Mother, as you are the Empreſs of all the Eaſtern part of the world, foraſmuch as I will not own the general name till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your Deceaſe; and all you my Lords and Barons of the Prity Counſel, and you alſo my grave and rederend Iudges, whoſe power and authority requireth you to do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice according to the due adminiſtration of
<pb facs="tcp:55822:82"/>the Statutes of this Realm, I do therefore demand juſtice upon the ſhameleſs Accuſer at the Bar, <hi>Radamentus</hi> and his Concubine, through whoſe means I was in peril of my life, and led ſeven times to the Gallows to he executed.</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>The Councels and Iudges hearing the words of the Empreſs, were all aſtoniſht to hear ſuch wiſdom from a woman; then all the Iudges and Counſellours ſtood up and call'd <hi>Radamentus: Radamentus,</hi> your evil life and converſation is very apparent to the Court, and your helliſh conſpiracies and notorious actions which here this day you are accus'd of, are publick Evidences againſt you at the Bar; and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law we do all here with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vote pronounce Sentence againſt you and your Concubine, that you ſhall be taken away from this place to the place from whence you came, and from thence to be drawn at two horſes tails throughout the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the place of Execution, which ſhall be under the common Gallows, and there to be burnt to aſhes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:84"/>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>The Empreſs having now out-lived her mortal Enemy old <hi>Radamentus,</hi> ſhe began a moſt happy and glorious Reign, her own Mother eſtéem'd her as her onely joy; the Nobles of the Land did honour her greatly for her excellent Learning and Wiſdom, the Subjects did almoſt adore her for the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refy of her Iuſtice, and the moderation of her Language, her Crown then began to flouriſh upon her head, and her Name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpread over all the face of the earth, and the longer ſhe did reign, the more her glory did ſhine; her Mother the old Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs lived till ſhe ſaw, that what for her Beauty, and what for her Learning, the bordering Nations round about did almoſt give divine reverence unto her; and in the heighth of this flouriſhing Peace, the old Empreſs dyed and bequeathed her own Crown and Royal Scopter for to be put
<pb facs="tcp:55822:85"/>upon <hi>Sabrina's</hi> head in this world, and a Crown of Glory in the world to come. <hi>Sabrina</hi> after this did Celebrate her Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in the greateſt Triumph which can be imaginable; ſhe alſo erected a moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monument, wherein ſhe interred the body of her Mother, with this Inſcription written on it:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Within this Monument interr'd here lies</l>
                     <l>The onely Mother of Sabrina the wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Who counſell'd was by Radamentus ſway,</l>
                     <l>To take Sabrina's precious life away:</l>
                     <l>But time and fortune favour'd her at laſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Life was ſav'd, and Radamentus loſt.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sabrina</hi> the young Empreſs having buried the old Empreſs in ſuch ſtate, was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded above all her predeceſſors: for never was ſuch a Monument erected before. Now <hi>Sabrina</hi> being Empreſs of all the Eauerne part of the World, began to grow very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:55822:86"/>and great, for all people gave her reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and did homage unto her: Kings and Princes ſent her rich preſents, and came from ſarre Counteys to viſit and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment her; but more eſpecially to hear her grave wiſdom, and to ſée the excellency of her Arts and Sciences, which bad ſo much ſpread over the whole world; ſhe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the greateſt Philoſopher that was in thoſe dayes in the world, ſhe continually keeping all ſorts of Profeſſours and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that ſo ſhe might thereby know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gitables, as Plants, Hearb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Roots, Leaves, and Trées: ſhe kept four thouſand Stables of Horſes, which were on purpoſe for her own Attendance; there was no Nation at war and variance with her but onely one, and they were the <hi>Tarters;</hi> ſo that now to prevent their Incroachment upon her moſt rich and plentiful Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhe choſe a fifth man out of all her Empire to build a brazen Wall betwéen her and her Enemies, about fiftéen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles long, and at every ten miles end ſhe cauſed to be built a ſtrong and famous Caſtle, wherein ſhe plac't ten thouſand men for to keep guard againſt the ſaid Tartars,
<pb facs="tcp:55822:86"/>which were People inhabiting in a poor and barren Countrey; for they fought not to revenge any quarrel or injury done to them, but méerly for ſome of the Gold and Riches this glorious <hi>Sabrina</hi> had, and to ſée if they could get into any of her plentifull Countreys to inhabit, for all her Countreys were golden Valleys both for profit and pleaſure: and though this brazen Wall was built and ſtrongly made, yet the fury of the Tartars was ſo iuraged, that they broke over, according to the old Proverb, <hi>Hunger will break through ſtone walls:</hi> and for thrée hours time there was a mortal Battle; but the young Empreſs <hi>Sabrina</hi> had a Champion in her Army called <hi>Gorgon,</hi> a Gyant you muſt conceive he was, for he was ſeven Cabits high, the Club that he bore was like the maſt of a Ship, his Helmet was made of Braſs, weighing an hundred ſhekels of Iron; this Gyant fought moſt courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and made lanes through the Army of the Lartars, that all dreaded and feared the place where he came: And on on a time it happening, that this Gyant was in the heat of the Battle, and being extream hot, he went to the main Ocean to drink, and to
<pb facs="tcp:55822:87"/>refreſh himſelf, and in the vehemency of his draught, he ſwallowed a Souldiers Knapſack full of Linnen, which made it ſwim, and he ſpate at it as if it had béen but a mote in his glaſs; but finding himſelf not very well, he ſent for the Empreſs Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who hearing the great Champion was not well, made what expedition he could to diſit him, and ſeeing him in ſuch a ſad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, he cauſed a Ladder for to be put down his Threat into his Belly, which was a uſual thing or cuſtome in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, eſpecially to ſuch men of ſuch vaſte and great ſtature, and commanded his Man to go down the Ladder into his belly, and there for to ſée if he could finds and know by his skill and good diſcretion what was the cauſe of his grief and heavineſs; but his man would not venture to go down, except he had a Link in his hand; and thereupon he lighted a good blazing Torch, and down he goes: But he had not deſcended downe above two ſteps, but the breath of the Gyant ariſing from his ſmoaking Gorge did very much dimnifle the light of his Link, and to recruit the light again, he ſmote it upon the rounds of the Ladder, which reduced the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:87"/>Gyant to ſuch an extream cough, that with the extremity thereof he had a very ſtrong vomit, that by the force and ſtrength thereof, he drove the fellow out of his belly, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lighted above ten foot from his mouth.</p>
                  <p>But no ſooner was the Fellow out of the Gyants belly, but he ran away in a great ſweat to his maſter, and told him, that he would not take half his Eſtate to go about the ſame Cure again. Nevertheleſs, the Gyant became very well afterwards, and built twelve famous Pillars, upon every Pillar he built a Caſtle, upon every Caſtle twelve Towers, and upon every Tower ſpacious Gardens, whereby a Lady of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure might have taken much delight in: But whether you may take this to be incredible or no, Ile leave that to your judgement.</p>
                  <p>But now as for the noble renowned P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in ceſs, the became ſo famous by her own State Policy, and by the aſſiſtance of that Gyant in victorious Battles, that moſt Princes in all that part of the world became her Tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, all being in ſubjection to her: and ſhe being counted the greateſt Beauty that lived in thoſe dayes, ſhe was obtained by <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Blag of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and eſpouſed his Wife, that when the ſtrength of his deny and the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:88"/>excellent wiſdom of this Empreſs, were joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one Politick body, they remain'd the ſole terrour of all the earth for many years together; but in the end were both deprived from Crowns and Kingdoms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the great and triumphant Wedding between the young Empreſs and Alexander King of Egypt, and of the unfortunate ſucceſſes that after enſued in his Dominions.</head>
                  <p>NOw in the beginning of <hi>April,</hi> when the earth had got on her Summer livery, and adorned with her flouriſhing wonted orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Alexander</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> deſigned his purpoſe to the Realm of <hi>Epirus,</hi> for he had heard ſay, there lived an Empreſs whoſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom exceeded all the Kings and Princes both adjacent and far remote, and the fame of that Empreſs invited him thither; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he prepared his Horſes and Chariots, with his Camels and Dromedaries laden with the richeſt Merchandire, Gold and Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els that was in all that part of the world, and proſecuted his deſign until he arrived in the Kingdom of <hi>Epirus,</hi> where young <hi>Sabrina</hi> the Empreſs maintained her chiefeſt reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and ſhe hearing of his coming, cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:55822:88"/>her Heraulds to proclaim in all Cities, Towns, and Corporations, that the great King of <hi>Egypt</hi> was coming to her Court, and alſo prepar'd her ſelf in perſon to meet him: ſhe rode in a rich and ſtately Chariot drawn by ſix milk white Steeds, with Trappings of Gold, and twelve Ladies of Honour with Palms in their hands on each ſide the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot; twelve Lord Barons marcht before bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rophies, in each of which there was artificially wrought a Garland of red Roſes, with all ſorts of inſtruments of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. King <hi>Alexander</hi> eſpying the Banners diſplayed in the Air, immediately knew that it was the Empreſs, and thereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Nobles to drive hard; and when 05 the King was come near to the Empreſs, and beheld her in all her glory, he was aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, and ſaid to himſelf, O Beauty incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable! ſeeming Deity, thou doeſt want nothing of all the excellencies of a woman, nor in thee has nature fail'd in any thing, but that it made thée mortal; ſo in as come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a grace, and in as brave a deportment as ever paſt between King and Quéen, they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted each other, and in a moſt triumphant ſtate marched unto her Royal Palace, where no delight was wanting: The young King
<pb facs="tcp:55822:89"/>had not been there above a week, but what by the Beauty, and what by the moſt mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vellous wiſdom he ſaw and heard from the Princeſs, he was even ſo raviſhed, that many times he knew not what he did; but it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in an evening, that <hi>Alexander</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſaw the Empreſs walking in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and thought it a fit opportunity to ſpeak unto her; ſo ſtept into the Walk, and ſaid unto the Empreſs, Moſt amiable, beauteous, wiſe, and learned Madam, by your Beauty I am raviſht, and at your wiſdom I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſht, even that my ſenſes are bereaved from me! Great Goddeſs, if I do not obtain one boon from your Grace, I ſhall live a captive to love, and a bond-ſlave to deſire; the thing which I crave is of no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. The Empreſs in a moſt Virgin-like and comely behaviour anſwered the King, being amorous of him alſo: My graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord and renowned Prince, whatſoever your requeſt is 'tis granted already. Then ſaid the King, O moſt fair and prudentiall Queen, nothing do I deſire more then onely to make you Queen and ſole Miſtris of all <hi>Egypt.</hi> The Empreſs being wiſe, conſidered the King to be a great Prince, amiable in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, wiſe and comely in behaviour, granted
<pb facs="tcp:55822:89"/>his requeſt: For ſhe underſtood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that matching with ſuch a great Prince as <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſhe ſhould become the greateſt Empreſs in the world, adding both powers together; and thereupon ſhe gave him h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hand upon it, and the day was appointed when the Marriage ſhould be Celebrated between theſe two great Potentates; all the Kings, Princes, Dukes, and Ladies in all the bordering Countreys round about were at the Wedding, except the King of <hi>Syra,</hi> who alwayes was an Antagoniſt to <hi>Alexander,</hi> whom all thoſe Princes now began to fear, in regard his Dominions were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by the Marriage with the wiſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; and his Power began to increaſe ſo, that he ſwayed the one half of the world, but his Enemy the King of <hi>Syra</hi> ſwayed the other; ſo that between them both the whole Univerſe was governed. The Marriage being ended, never King or Queen did flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in more peace and unity for ſeven years then they did; for through the daily compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of this wiſe and renowned Empreſs, <hi>Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> was much bettered, and by her wiſdom his wits were illuminat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d; and ſhe made him a body Politick, inſomuch that he would b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tive of all Ambaſſadours to
<pb facs="tcp:55822:90"/>know the nature of their Countreys, the diſpoſition of their people, the majeſty of their Kings, and the wayes of their Wars. He alwayes kept a great Army, but under ſtrict orders, and much ſeverity; he was feared by all the Kings about him, onely the King of <hi>Syra,</hi> who daily watcht how he might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize him; he was lovely, valiant, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet; he was courteous to all people, loving to his Empreſs, of whom he had begot two Sens; his love did alwayes burn and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo far towards his Empreſs, that being in <hi>Egypt</hi> upon a time, leaving his Empreſs in <hi>Epirus,</hi> he would every morning run up to the top of a mountain, and look ſtedfaſtly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Epirus,</hi> and would ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd this Meſſage to her by the Moon feignedly.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Sweet <hi>Sabrina,</hi> when ſhall we in ſeats</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of thoſe bleſt ſhades quench and renew our heats;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There ſhall the Queen of Love and Innocence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beauty and Nature baniſh all offence:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In thy ſweet preſence ſhall I there behold</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy bared Snow, and thy unbraded Gold;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There my enfranchiz'd hand on every ſide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall o're thy naked poliſht Ivory ſlide;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:90"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No curtain there, though of tranſparent Lawn</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall be before thy Virgin treaſure drawn;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the rich minde to the enquiring eye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Expos'd ſhall ready ſtill for mintage lye:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we will coyn young Cupid there a bed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Roſes, and freſh mirtles ſhall be ſpread</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Under the cooler ſhades of Cypreſs Groves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our pillows of the doun of Venus Doves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whereon our panting love we'l gentle lay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In the faint reſpites of our active play,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſo our ſlumbers may in dreams have leaſure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To tell the nimble fancy of our pleaſure;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſo our ſouls that cannot be imbrac't,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall the imbraces of our bodies taſte;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mean while the publick ſtream ſhall drown the ſhore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Th'inamour'd chirping wood-quire ſhall adore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In varied Tunes the Deity of Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The gentle blaſts of Weſtern windes ſhall move</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The trembling leaves, and through the cloſe boughs breathe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Still Muſick, whilſt we reſt our ſelves beneath</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their dancing ſhades, till a ſoft murmurre ſent</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From ſouls intranc't in amorous languiſhment,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rouze us and ſhoot into our eyes freſh fire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till we in their ſweet extaſie expire:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then as they empty be that lately bore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into the common Treaſure all her ſtore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:91"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Flyes'bout the painted fields with nimble Wing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deflowring the freſh Virgins of the ſpring:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So will I riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e all the ſweets that dwell</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In my delicious paradiſe, and ſwell</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My bag with honey drawn forth by the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of fervent kiſſes, from each ſpicy flower;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'le ſeize the Roſe buds in their perfum'd bed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Violet Knots like curious Maces ſpread</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O're all the Garden, taſte the ripened Cherry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Apple, Apricock, and Coral Berry</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then will I viſit with a wandring kiſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Vale of Lillies, and the Bower of Bliſs;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And where the beauteous Region doth divide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into two milky wayes my lips ſhall ſlide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Down thoſe ſmooth Alleys, wearing as I go</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A track for Lovers in the printed ſnow;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thence climing o're thy ſwelling Appenine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Retire into thy Grove of Eglantine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where I will all thoſe raviſht ſweets diſtil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Through loves Alembique, &amp; with chymick skill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From the mixt Maſs, one ſovereign balm derive</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And bring that great Elixure to thy hive.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now in more ſubtle wreaths I will entwine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My lovely Thighs, my Legs, and Arms with thine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou like a ſea of milk ſhalt lye diſplay'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whilſt I the ſmooth qualm Ocean doth invade</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ſuch a Tempeſt, as when <hi>Jove</hi> of old</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fell down on <hi>Danae</hi> in a ſtorm of Gold;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55822:91"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet my tall pine ſhall in the Cyprian ſtrait</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bide ſafe at Anchor, and unlade her freight;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My rudder with thy bold hand, like a try'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And skilful Pilot, thou ſhalt ſteer and guide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Bark into loves Channel, where it ſhall</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dance as the bounding Waves doth riſe and fall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then ſhall thy circling armes imbrace and clip</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My willing body and thy balmy lip,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bathe me in juice of kiſſes, whoſe perfume</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like a Religious Incenſe ſhall conſume,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſend up holy vapours, to thoſe powers</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That bleſs our Loves &amp; crown our ſportful hours.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now Wedlock bonds unwreath our twiſted Loves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We ſeek no midnight Arbours, no dark Groves</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To hide our Kiſſes, there the hated name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Husband, Wife, luſt, modeſt, chaſte, or ſhame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are vain and empty words, whoſe very ſound</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Was never heard in the Elizian ground:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All things are lawful there that may delight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nature, or unreſtrained appetite;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like and enjoy, to will and act is one,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We onely ſue where loves rites are not done.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Theſe and ten thouſand ſuch expreſſions this brave King <hi>Alexander</hi> did uſe towards his renowned Empreſs; but fortune not willing to favour him did caſt a cloud over this pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of vertue; for no ſooner had he ſet his
<pb facs="tcp:55822:92"/>Kingdom of <hi>Egypt</hi> and arrived again in <hi>Epy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> but there came a Herauld at Armes from the King of <hi>Syra</hi> to challenge him to the Field, that upon the happy ſucceſs of one bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, the whole univerſe lay on't, for they two governed all the other Kings in the world: <hi>Alexander</hi> with a brave courageous ſpirit an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Herauld, I look't for the King of <hi>Syra</hi> in the Field long ago, I wonder his Chariot Wheels are ſo heavy in driving; and bid him meet upon the Downs of <hi>Opher,</hi> where I will be in perſon to aſſail him and his ten Legions; and preſently commanded his Drums to beat, and his Trumpets to ſound, with other Inſtruments of War, and ſo marched out with his Army, taking his leave of his Royal Princeſs, and his two Sons, with ſhowres of tears betwixt them both, ſo parted the one from the other with heavy hearts. When brave King <hi>Alexander</hi> was arrived upon the Downs of <hi>Opher,</hi> he plac't his men in Battle of Aray, and began to admoniſh them in theſe words; Moſt brave and warlike Souldiers, both Epirians and Egyptians, I exhort you this day to be of good courage, and fight manfully, your Cauſe is juſt and right; for the <hi>Syrans</hi> are coming againſt us without cauſe, and we are upon
<pb facs="tcp:55822:92"/>our defence, and this great Battle is the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for the whole world; in the very heat of Battle think to your ſelves that you do ſee the grave Senators of <hi>Epyrus</hi> bowing down their hoary heads, praying for your good ſucceſs; think that you do hear the Prayers of your Fathers, Mothers, Wives, and Children for you; and know that whoſoever intends to ſée their friends again, muſt this day ranſome himſelf with his Sword: think to your ſelves that if the <hi>Syrans</hi> doth vanquiſh, us how that my head will be plac't upon a Poll, and pitcht up in the Market, place, and my Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hung up, two in <hi>Egypt</hi> and two in <hi>Epirus;</hi> our Cities and Towns burnt and turned to aſhes, our Maidens and Virgins deflowred, our Childrens brains daſht againſt the walls, and our young men ſlain and murthered, and the brand of ſcorn upon our Kingdoms for perpetuity. And on the other ſide, if we do get the day, honour and renown ſhall be upon our heads, and the glories of <hi>Syra</hi> ſhall come into <hi>Epirus;</hi> Gold and Silver ſhall be your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the favour of your Prince you ſhall have to eternity. The Souldiers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Moſt great King, if the Gold of <hi>Opher</hi> will make you glorious, if the Treaſures of <hi>Syra</hi> will make you great, and if the ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:55822:93"/>of our Army will make you conſiderable both at home and abroad: be aſſured great King, you are this day the Maſter of all the Univerſe, for here is not a Souldier but at your command will cut his Fathers Throat, and ſheath his Sword in his Brothers Blood, to rob the Gods and pull the Temples down, all this will they do if you command them. By this time there was but one Fields breadth between the two Armies, all Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers, Trees, and Hedges were levelled even with the ground, Lions and Bears were ſeen to come out of the Woods, as of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to devour dead Carkaſſes, Vultures which are ravening Birds, did darken the Air, Lightning and Thunder came down that did melt the heads of the Foot-mens Spears, and ſinged the Hair on their Heads, and the Horſe Manes. King <hi>Alexander</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Army into four parts, his right Wing conſiſted of ten thouſand, conducted by ten Kings, the Forlorn-Hope were five thouſand, the left Wing were ten thouſand, conducted by ten <hi>Epirian</hi> Lords, the main Body was led by brave <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf; the Battle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan hot, and ſharp, the Forlorn-Hope of the <hi>Epirians</hi> were driven back to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> main Body; then advanced <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf, and the
<pb facs="tcp:55822:93"/>Battle began to be mortal, the diſpute old hold till twelve a Clock, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell on both ſides above eight thouſand: In the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon the Battle began again, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture fell upon the <hi>Epirians,</hi> for in four hours time <hi>Alexander</hi> was fain to quit the Field, being totally defeated and moſt of his men ſlain. <hi>Alexander</hi> was fain to throw his Crown upon the ground, becauſe he would not be known, and eſcaped by Sea in a poor Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermans Boat, and ſailed into <hi>Epirus;</hi> and at the Haven where he deſigned to Land, there his Royal Empreſs was waiting when any Ship would come in with news; and at laſt ſhe eſpied in a poor Fiſhermans Boat King <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf; at which ſight, fear ſmote her to the heart, that ſhe ſwoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed upon the thought that the King was utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown: but <hi>Alexander</hi> took her up in his armes and kiſt her, with a ſhowre of tears bedewing their Princely Cheeks; but there was no remedy, for their Kingdoms was wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from them, and they forced to ſlye into an uninhabited Iſland, wherein they ſpent the remnant of their dayes with three other pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Kings. Soon after <hi>Alexander</hi> dyed, and his Empreſs, who in a Sepulchre which he hewed out himſelf, they were both interred;
<pb facs="tcp:55822:94"/>on which was written this following Epitaph.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Within this Houſe of Stone here lyes</l>
                     <l>The King of Egypt, who was call'd the Wiſe:</l>
                     <l>Likewiſe that glorious and illuſtrious Queen</l>
                     <l>Of the Epirians here is to be ſeen;</l>
                     <l>Who from all Right and Juſtice were debarr'd,</l>
                     <l>When Syrans King in Battle with him Warr'd.</l>
                  </q>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55822:94"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
